Okay.
Good morning.
So,
these next two classes today and on
Saturday will be the most intense
classes
of the series of the seminar.
And
um
the reason why
is
that
um we will we will go from Canto 24
and we will read every line up to Canto
33 to the end of the Divine Comedy.
There's a very good reason why I'm doing
this, okay? But before I start, are
there any issues from yesterday? Any
questions from yesterday that you would
like to me to address? Uh yes.
>> So, uh in Canto 24,
uh
line line 83,
he added, "Now this coin is well
examined, and now we know its alloy and
its weight. But tell me, do you have it
in your purse?" And the reason why I
have a question about this is that in
Christianity, and especially in
Catholicism, it's said that money is the
root of all evil. So, why would Dante in
heaven talking about faith compare his
faith to a coin and his self to a purse?
>> Okay. So, you're jumping ahead. We
actually have not come to this section
yet, okay? So, that's something we will
do today. So, so could you please wait
um until we get to this section, okay?
Thank you.
Any other questions? Uh yes.
>> So, in Canto 11, um
that's the one where
um
in line five he says, uh one was set on
the priesthood, and in line eight it
said one labored tangled in the delights
of flesh. So, that's Canto 11, lines
five and eight. Um he seems to be doing
almost like a
uh talking about the the bad qualities
between the mind, body, and spirit, it
seems like.
Um and so it seems to me
that he's like calling out the Catholic
Church perhaps as like tangled in the
delights of flesh. Would the delights of
flesh be sex?
Um and so it's almost
>> Yeah, and and what is your
interpretation?
>> So it seems like he's he's calling out
one after the other. Like he calls out
um
in line four like uh
Uh one meant to plunder,
one to politic, one labored tangled in
the delights of flesh, one was fully
bent on indolence. And so I got this as
like all the ways you could corrupt the
mind with the sophists, like I'm going
to sell you knowledge, but knowledge is
free, we can just pick up a book. The
second is the body, I can sell the body
um and
um that would be uh prostitution. But
then the other would be the spirit, the
selling of salvation. And I didn't know
if he was like
calling out the Catholic Church, which
seemed like I know that he has problems
with the Catholic Church, but I didn't
think he'd call them out.
[clears throat] So
>> He's actually pretty blatant about this.
Um throughout the Divine Comedy, he will
refer to the idea of indulgences. Okay,
the idea of indulgences is
Okay, let's just say you're really bad
person. [clears throat]
And but you are filthy rich.
And you're like, okay, I'm I'm going to
die now,
and I know I'm going to hell, but is
there a loophole? And the Catholic
Church says, yes, it's called
indulgences, where if you pay a certain
fine or contribution donation to
Catholic Church, the Catholic Church
will reduce your penance in purgatory.
Um so this is a very common practice at
this time.
The Catholic Church is using it to
finance things like St. Peter's
Basilica.
Okay?
Um and so Donny is uh criticizing the
sprout. And in fact,
um
the more we go into heaven, the more
blatant the criticism is.
Okay? So, that's something to watch out
for. So, thank you for the question. Any
more questions before we start class.
Okay. So, again, we have a lot to do
today and on Saturday. So, let me set
the scene, okay?
Um Donny will die in year 1321 after
having completed the Divine Comedy.
Um the cantos that we're reading
today and on Saturday, um the last 10
cantos,
he's writing this a year or 2 years
before he dies. Okay? He's busy writing
like three lines a day.
And um I want you to close your eyes and
picture where Dante is in his life
and in history. Okay? It's like 1320,
1319. He's exiled from Florence, his
home. And not only his home, but the
home of his ancestors, of his entire
family.
His blood enemies, the Black Guelphs,
control Florence and they have
confiscated his property. So, he's he's
lost all his wealth.
Um he has no hope of ever returning to
Florence. The Pope, Boniface, is the one
who's conspiring against him. Okay? So,
you have the Pope angry at you.
And yes, you are living in a nice
mansion sponsored given to you by a
patron of yours, but you are a beggar.
And
at this time in your life,
you know you're going to die soon,
and you are filled with despair because
you know you're probably never to home
again to Florence. Even if you do go
home to Florence, you will never
re-reclaim the glory that your family
once had. Um
and you finish both Inferno and
Purgatorio. They've been both published
as manuscripts and they're being
circulated around. And the feedback
you've been getting is very positive.
But
you don't know
what the reception will be. You don't
know if people will truly appreciate and
honor
your contribution.
And
um
you you're also afraid of Catholic
Church because you've been very critical
of the Catholic Church. It's very easy
for one of your enemies, the Black
Guelph, to point out this manuscript,
the Divine Comedy, give it to the Pope
and say, "This is heresy. He is
criticizing the church. He is promoting
ideas that um are heretical, okay?" So,
this is the very bottom of Dante's life.
And he's got another year or 2 years
before he dies.
And at this point in history, the
closest analogies we have are Jesus,
right? So, imagine the Last Supper.
You're Jesus and you know you're going
to die
the next day. You know that Judas
Iscariot, who is sitting with you at the
Last Supper, by the way, one of your
closest disciples, he will betray you
to the um
um
uh Pharisees or the Sadducees, I can't
remember, okay? But you'll be betrayed
by one of your closest followers.
And the only fate that awaits you is
your painful, agonizing, very slow
death, okay? Being crucified is one one
the worst things that can happen to you
because you may not know this, but when
you are being crucified on the cross,
what kills you is not um the bleeding.
What kills you is the fact that you're
too weak to hold your head high.
So, you slowly suffocate to death. And
it's like a 3 to 4-day process.
It's the most painful way to die, and
that's why the Romans practice this,
okay? You know this is going to happen
to you.
So, how do you feel at this point, okay?
And this gives you insight to how
Dante's feeling at this point.
Another analogy is Moses,
the prophet of God,
uh
the one who
uh rescued the Jews from E- from slavery
in Egypt and took them to promised land,
which is Jerusalem.
>> [snorts]
>> And for 40 years, you, Moses, have been
wandering and the Jews have been
wandering around in the desert.
And at this end of 40 years, God comes
to you in a vision says,
"Moses, you've sacrificed everything to
free your people from captivity.
Um
you will not walk into the promised
land."
Okay? You can see it, but you will not
walk into it.
So, imagine how Moses is feeling at this
time, okay?
And so,
what
is
magical, what is truly courageous about
Dante is that in this time of his
greatest despair, when he has absolutely
no evidence,
no proof that the Divine Comedy will, in
fact, change the world,
he chooses
to embrace faith,
hope,
and love.
And then he writes these next 10 cantos
that will forever change human history.
These next
what we'll be reading today on Saturday
are
It's shocking.
Um and it is magical.
And it and
I don't think anyone has truly
revealed
what Dante is thinking, okay? So, think
of these last
10 cantos as Dante's will and testament
to humanity. What his hope for is
humanity.
And again, no one has really
in-depth revealed this will and
testament. So, think of this as just the
intention of the universe where Dante
finishes in 1321 and then 900 900 years
later, we gather in Beijing to reveal to
the world
his will and testament.
Um and the reason why is
today, we really need to truly
understand
uh Dante's thinking. So,
there will be three rules for next two
classes, okay?
The the first rule,
uh which is the most important, is
Okay.
Stay focused.
We are here in order to reveal the will
and testament of Dante. It's never been
done before.
And it has to be done, okay? That's that
is our mission for next 2 days. We are
going to read Dante line by line and
truly understand what his message is to
humanity. And it is shocking, it's
revolutionary, and it will be cathartic
for us, okay? So, stay focused on this.
Second thing is to fully participate.
Many of you have come a long way to be
here in order to experience Dante.
The only way you can make the most of
your experience is by fully
participating.
Um yesterday we had
two new members of this class start to
participate and that led to richer
discussion.
Believe that each and every one of you,
you do matter and your contribution does
make this class better, okay? More
lively, more rich, uh more imaginative.
All right? So, please try to participate
as much as possible. And the third thing
is to
act with
>> [snorts]
>> faith,
hope, and love.
Okay?
In other words, put away for these next
two classes your ego,
your fear,
and your doubt.
Okay?
This class is meant to be one of faith,
hope, and love.
I understand that in school you're
taught to be critical. You're taught to
um
think critically and read critically and
to introspect, into interrogate, okay?
I'm just saying put away that
training for the next two days and let's
just focus on acting with faith, hope,
and love.
So, what we're going to do first is
figure out what is faith, what is hope,
and what is love. What we discussed last
class is that faith is ultimately an act
of imagination.
Okay?
Um what Paul tells us is that there is a
plan.
What Dante will tell us
is we are the plan.
Do you understand the difference?
Paul's like, "There is a plan." Dante's
like, "We are the plan."
Our imagination is what animates the
universe.
Okay?
What we What we're going to learn today
is that hope. And this is like really
interesting is
What is hope? Hope is
arrogance.
This is a really key concept to Dante,
and that's why again he's shocking, he's
revolutionary.
If you truly want to change the world
for better, you need hope. But hope is
not humility. Hope is not believing God
will change the world for you.
Hope is arrogance, which is say, "I can
change the world for the better."
Okay? So, when we say hope, it means
like together, we will reveal Dante's
will and testament,
and show the world how humanity can be
better off. Okay? It's an act of hope,
but it's really an act of arrogance.
And for for Dante, that's very, very
crucial. Uh yes? Did you have a
question?
>> Yeah, are you getting there?
Are you getting there because one hopes
introspectively, and so you have the I
and the ego? You can't I can't hope for
you. Like
I'm if even if I'm hoping for you, I'm
the one that's hoping. And so, are you
saying it's arrogance because it's
I-focused?
>> Okay. So, again, let's go back to the
um
image of Dante alone in his room,
writing The Divine Comedy by himself,
while in exile and isolation, right?
There is no evidence that The Divine
Comedy will become the greatest work of
literature in human history. There's
absolutely no
evidence at all.
And if you were humble, he'd be like,
"You know what? The chances are
that
um whatever I write will have
made an impact on the people around me,
but it won't really change the world for
the better."
In which case,
if that humility, he'd just be like, "I
give up because it's not really worth my
while."
Right? What hope is to say,
"I see
that 900 years from now,
there's going to be people
in China, in Beijing,
who will read me and who will worship me
and who will love me."
Okay? That's an act of arrogance.
Right?
It's an act of hope, but you think about
it, it's really an act of arrogance to
say like, "I am the most important
person in the world, and I will live
forever eternally." And that hope is
what allows him to survive for the next
one or two years and put all his focus
and energy into completing the Divine
Comedy. Without hope, without arrogance,
he could not have done so.
Right?
Uh yes?
>> How would you say this is different from
his ego?
>> Excuse me?
>> Uh how would you say this uh
>> Yeah, that's a great question. Okay.
>> hope is
>> Right. Because
what he's doing is he's trying to change
the world.
Do you understand? So, it's an act of he
he's gifting himself to the world. He's
saying like, "My last year or two years
it is not to enjoy myself. It is not to
go around, have dinners, where all these
dukes, these princes are praising my
poetry." Because he could do that,
right? He could be like, "You know what?
I've written the Inferno, I've written
the Purgatorio. It's fantastic, and I'm
getting all these patrons, and they all
want because they all want to be in my
poetry. So, I'll just go around to these
different courts, and I will sing their
praises, and they'll give me a lot of
money, and I can enjoy myself. And no,
he's like, "No, I'm going to stay in my
room
away from all the attention, and just
focus on finishing the Divine Comedy."
Okay? And when you actually read the
last two cantos,
it is extremely arrogant,
and but it's also an extremely selfless
act, where he is trying to show humanity
a better future, right?
It it's
it's like Jesus at the Last Supper, and
he knows he's going to make the ultimate
sacrifice for humanity, but he's
arrogant about it. He's like, "Only I
can save humanity. Only I can redeem
humanity."
Right? And whereas Moses
Moses, again,
he
traveled in the desert for 40 years,
and God says to him,
"Well,
um sorry, you can't walk on the promised
land. You can't set foot on the promised
land. You can see it from afar, but
that's it." And Moses is
doesn't matter.
Um but the the the Jews will remember me
as the greatest prophet. And it is it is
true. He read the Bible, he is the
greatest prophet, okay?
All right? So, it's an act of um
arrogance, but it's also an act of
selflessness, okay? All right? All
right, yes?
>> Um so, something I would I like to ask
is that when Dante was doing all of
this, when he was doing this selfless
sacrifice, was he doing it with the
expectation that it will come to
fruition?
>> Uh that's what hope is, yes.
>> So, if he is doing it with the
expectation that it's all coming to
fruition, then isn't he being a little
bit
uh heretical, because he is expecting
God to do something for him?
>> Yes, like as I will show you in the next
two cantos, Divine Comedy is pure
heresy, okay? If you are a Catholic
church
priest and you are able to read Divine
Comedy in year 1321, you'd be very, very
angry. All right? But again, there's
nothing you can do about it because you
understand in your heart that all art is
comes from God as the source.
Okay? So, there is both um anger at
Dante, but there's also deep fear and
respect towards Dante. Uh yes?
>> Out of curiosity, how do you think they
would have rationalized that at the time
seeing that there's this work that
criticizes the Catholic Church, but that
it's God's will to criticize the
Catholic Church?
>> Right. So, that's a great question. In
psychology, there's a phrase called
cognitive dissonance.
Right? So, you read Divine Comedy and
you're a Catholic priest and you're
like, "Oh, he's praising God. He's
praising the church, the bride of God,
right?" So, this is cognitive
dissonance. That's why Dante is so
powerful because only if you truly
understand him, can you truly
uh appreciate what he's doing.
Okay? Because remember where we are. We
are
um Dante is now
studied everything he got from Beatrice
and now he's being tested by
Peter, James, and John, the three
apostles, right? He's also being tested
in an academic setting uh that has been
approved by the Catholic Church. So, you
if you read this on the surface,
um then you have to think that Dante is
a very pious individual. And quite
honestly, the Catholic Church today
believes Dante is a true Christian,
okay?
Like like it's
I mean I mean what what I will teach you
is that he's heretical, but you have to
have a very nuanced understanding of him
in order to appreciate this. Okay? Does
that make sense?
Okay? Uh Uh yes?
>> I'm not talking about his heresy in the
eyes of the Catholic Church. I'm talking
about his heresy in the eyes of his own
construction of his own belief of God.
So, according to his definition, God is
ineffable. You cannot expect him to do
something and he will do it. However,
right here he is expecting God to reward
him for his effort.
>> Um okay. So,
um we've been
um
learning about Dante for the past 4 days
and it's pretty obvious to me from this
comment that you made that you don't
really understand
what's what's being taught here. What
what what what Dante is really trying to
teach.
God is all-loving, all-forgiving.
Uh
I I
we we will we will look at the look at
this, okay? Just just keep your doubts
um in check. Let's let's just focus on
what he's going to tell us. All right,
yes?
>> Oh, I'm just really interested how like
the Catholic Church at the time
responded to Dante. Like were there any
works that they published or like um
speeches that they made since Yes.
>> Okay, so some historical context. Why
Dante is able to do what he's doing is
because the world is in turmoil. Because
the Catholic Church is split. There are
in fact two centers of the Catholic
Church, okay? There's one that uh is in
Rome, but there's also another in
Avignon. Um because the Holy Roman
Emperor has appointed another church,
okay? Uh so another pope. So, the thing
that turned up in the Catholic Church is
that
um they are at war with each other. It's
an internal civil war in the Catholic
Church. There are different different
factions and that's why Dante is able to
do what he's do because there's no
central authority in place.
>> They were too busy fighting each other.
>> They were too busy fighting each other,
exactly. Okay? All right? All right. So,
thank you, okay. All right. So, we have
a lot to do today, okay? So, let let's
get started, okay? All right.
So, remember where we are? Where
um Dante is being interrogated
by Peter on what faith is.
And um
Dante will first respond with Paul's
formulation, which is that faith is
evidence of things unseen, meaning
that
only faith can prove that certain things
exist, like God. You cannot through
science ever prove that God exists.
Okay? But then, what he will say that's
different from
Paul is that Paul is basically saying
there are things that
exist beyond our imagination.
So, let us be humble and obey God. Okay?
That That's what faith is. Faith is one
of compliance, one of acceptance. And
what Dante says is like, "No.
Everything comes from imagination, and
faith is an act of imagination. Without
the imagination,
um there could be no faith. Okay? It's
because we willingly, proactively
believe in something does it come true.
It is It is not true by itself. Okay?
So, this is a very important distinction
that Dante will continue to elaborate
on. All right. Uh so, let's continue.
>> Canto 24, verse 79.
And then I heard, "If all one learns
below as doctrine were so understood,
there would be no place for sophist's
cleverness."
This speech was breathed from that
enkindled love. He added,
"Now, this coin is well examined, and
now we know its alloy and its weight.
But tell me, do you have it in your
purse?" And I, "Indeed I do. So bright
and round that nothing in its stamp
leads me to doubt."
Next, from the deep light gleaming
there, I heard "What is the origin of
the dear gem that comes to you?"
>> Okay, stop. Okay, all right. So, um this
is a very interesting question, like,
okay, if the
um
Catholic Church is against money,
why is
Dante referring to
faith as a coin?
Right? It's a coin.
What's going on here?
Yes.
>> Could it be the indulgences that we're
selling? The like the indulgences you
mentioned before, so.
>> Oh, indulgences are evil, right?
>> Yeah.
>> Indulgences are like against everything
that Jesus had.
>> faith is a coin because you pay your way
into like believing or
um doing good things, maybe.
>> Oh, no, no. Um okay, anyone else?
>> Uh yeah, uh I don't know. I just try to
guess. Maybe because coin is is is
stands for money and for fortune because
during the back to that period we are
and church they just try to ask people
to pay the money to redeem their their
stains, so maybe
uh Dante is just saying the coin is uh
is something that the you know, the
church would have to to make use of to
try to let people to pay for it so that
they can redeem their sin to be uh be be
good.
>> Okay, why is it paradoxical to say that
faith is a coin?
Why is it paradoxical?
Uh yes?
>> Does it have anything to do with its
two-sidedness?
>> Okay, can you explain?
>> Um I was just thinking cuz the coin
usually has two sides and
um I'm not the most knowledgeable about
historical or the religious content, but
I was wondering if faith also is a
two-sided thing in a way.
>> Okay. All right. Why is
Okay, let's let's go on this, okay?
There's a paradox, right? Faith is a
coin. Why is that a paradox?
Uh I yes and then then then then then
you.
>> Well, a coin is something material and
faith is like just in the mind.
>> Exactly. Do you understand? Okay? Faith
is air. It's nothing.
Coin is material. But not only not only
is it material, what is it? It's also
heavy.
You understand?
If it's in your pocket, it's going to be
the most heavy thing in your pocket.
Right? So, this metaphor what it
what it reveals is that
faith is the heaviest thing in you.
It is the thing that anchors you. Does
that make sense? Okay? So, the I did the
coin isn't that it's money. The the
the I did the coin is that it's a heavy
valuable object inside of you. Uh
did did you have a comment or question?
>> I just wanted to build off uh
her comment cuz I do think it's
interesting because we talk about let's
say two sides of an argument, but
it's a paradox because faith is
one-sided.
>> Yeah. Okay. All right. Yes?
>> So, something that I find interesting is
a paradox that's not only evident here
in the Dubai community, but also in the
church as a whole. So, nowadays our
coins are made of like steel, made of
metals that are not so precious, so they
don't weight as much as this coin of
faith presumably does. And they
specifically asked Dante, like the
pilgrim Dante, about the coin's alloy.
And since it's heavy, even though it's
only a coin, I think it's reasonable to
assume that it might be made of gold, a
very precious
>> Well, after some in history, yes, they
are made of gold.
>> Well, what I'm what I'm saying is that
gold is a very precious metal and the
church, well, the church and Dante
himself, while simultaneously condemning
wealth, they are holding this
metaphorical gold coin in their pocket.
Why can't they pick another metaphor?
>> Uh or or or pick one then.
>> Um, well, I'm thinking maybe they can
maybe they can say like milk and honey,
the old metaphor.
>> Milk and honey? That's not
Uh, yeah yes?
>> [clears throat]
>> I think this coins well examine. There's
also a verse in the scripture that says
that gold will go through fire and faith
is like the gold that can withstand the
test of fire. I think maybe this is one
of the reasons
>> Yes, exactly. Thank you. Yes, yes.
That's right. Okay. Okay. All right. Uh,
thank you for that. Yes. So, that's why
it's important to read the footnotes.
Okay. Um,
yes. C- C- Can we keep on reading, um,
Carol?
>> Verse 90.
What is the origin of the dear gem that
comes to you? The gem on which all
virtues are founded. I, the Holy Ghost
abundant rain poured upon the parchments
old and new. That is the syllogism that
has proved with such
persuasiveness
that faith has truth. When set beside
that argument, all other demonstrations
seem to me obtuse.
>> Okay. So, uh, Peter asked him a
question, which is like
Faith is inside of you, but where does
it come from?
How do you have faith? What proves to
you
that God must exist? And what is his
answer?
W- Right, right, but but I'm saying like
like how what in your life proves that
the Holy Spirit must exist?
What did he say?
>> Holy Ghost abundant rain.
>> Excuse me?
>> The Holy Ghost abundant rain poured upon
>> What does it What's the rain doing?
What?
Yeah, you go you go you go ahead first.
>> So basically he's saying that the Holy
Ghost abundant rain poured upon
parchments old and new and here abundant
rain is water. Abundant rain is ink and
he is trying to say that the Holy Ghost
has inspired so many writings on
parchment old and new.
>> What is a parchment old and new?
>> New and Old Testament
>> Yes, yes and the Bible. If God didn't
exist,
how could you have a Bible, which is
this brilliant work of literature,
right? Who's giving hope and inspiration
to millions around the world and it's
persisted for thousands of years.
So, the Bible itself is proof that God
must exist. If you read the Bible,
especially Genesis, it is beautiful.
It's it's one of the greatest works of
literature in history, right?
And it is the Holy Ghost that infuses
himself, right? Like rain, it's a
metaphor, throughout the Holy Bible. So,
when the people who
who wrote the Bible, they were being
possessed by the Holy Ghost. That is
proof.
Okay?
Otherwise, you can't explain the Bible.
Okay, keep on going.
>> Verse 97.
I heard
the premises of old and new impelling
your conclusion, why do you hold these
to be the speech of God?
>> Okay, so it's like how do you know it's
truly the work of God, that these people
are speaking for God. Keep on going.
>> And I the proof revealing truth to me
relies on acts that happened. For such
miracles, nature can heat no iron, beat
no anvil.
Say, who assures you that those works
were real? Came the reply, the very
thing that needs proof, no thing else
attests these works to you.
I said, if without miracles the world
was turned to Christianity, that is so
great a miracle that all the rest are
not its hundredth part. For you were
poor and hungry when you found the field
and so sowed the good plant. Once a vine
and now a thorn."
>> Okay. So, again, what's happening is
that Peter continues to
interrogate and said, "How do you know
for a fact that the Bible is the word of
God?"
And what Don is says is,
"Well, in real life there's evidence."
What's the evidence?
Yes, sir?
>> The Bible.
>> What? But how do you know the Bible is
the word of God?
Uh yes?
>> Especially saying all these physical
things like parting the Red Sea and
stuff actually happened.
>> No, that's what he's saying.
Uh yes?
>> The fact that
>> [clears throat]
>> the whole world has turned to
Christianity.
>> Exactly. Can you please explain to me
how this happened? 2 billion people in
the world
are Christians, okay? Now, I I don't
mean to insult Christians, but when I
was growing up in Canada, everyone
around me was a Christian and they were
telling me about how Jesus Jesus
crucified himself on the cross.
And how
um God came to redeem us from our sins
like and I was like, "This makes no
logical sense, guys, okay? Do you even
know what you're talking about?"
Okay? For like decades of my life, even
when I was at Yale,
uh which was founded as a Christian
school,
I had no idea what was going on, okay?
So, to me it's a miracle that this very
confusing religion is able to
conquer the world. Where you have 2
billion people believing in it. That is
a miracle. And unless
you believe that it is the divine plan
of God, it's very hard to explain, okay?
Also, guys, I I I I I again I don't to
insult Christians, but
Jesus, what did he do exactly?
Right? I could understand if you if
there's a religion about Julius Caesar
or Genghis Khan or Alexander the Great
these or Napoleon because they did a
lot, right? I'm not sure what Jesus did.
Jesus
I mean, he was crucified on the cross
and that's it.
I mean
so so but like like like like I'm not
trying to like
prove that Christianity is like stupid
but I'm I'm going to show like there's
so many paradoxes in Christianity that
unless you accept that um
God exists and this is all part of the
divine plan it's hard to explain why
there are 2 billion Christians in the
world.
Does that make sense, guys?
>> And by the way, I want to add that I
don't feel insulted as a Christian.
>> Okay, right.
>> Um because I think the dialectics is
also part of the journey.
>> Right, right. Yeah. Yes?
>> I I think this is actually super great.
Like I think that I think that he's
being really smart here. This is a
really great argument of his, but I'm
not sure what he is trying to prove
here. Like his audience his audience are
all people who speak like Italian,
right? Audience are people who speak
Italian, who speak Latin, who can who
can read. And these people are going to
be educated people in Europe. And these
people are going to be Christian
already. So why is he proving their own
faith to them?
>> Okay.
Um
let's appreciate what's going on, okay?
In the year 1300
if you go to your priest and say to him
um how do we know
there's faith in the world?
And how do you how do we know that God
exists? And how do we
uh know the Bible is actually the word
of God? What would he tell you?
>> Maybe you are it's communicated.
>> Yeah, maybe maybe the Satan has taken
control of you, right? Maybe you're
speaking for Satan. That's literally
what they would say to you.
Right? And what Don is saying is like,
"No, guys, let's not do that. Let's
actually try to logically use our
imagination, figure this out, because we
can do that."
Right? You see the difference? It's
night and day.
You go to a priest like, you make a you
ask a question, "Satan is in you."
Like don't That's literally what would
happen.
Right? And now in the like how it's
like, "No, of course you should ask a
question. Let's try to figure this out
naturally. Okay? Let's use our
imagination." This is a revolution. It's
a heresy. Do you understand?
Okay? We we you take it for granted
today, but I'm not saying in the year
1300, okay? This is a This is
revolutionary. What's going on?
All right? And and for this to happen in
heaven, right? Not in a university, but
in heaven.
And it's Peter, the first Pope.
Right?
Okay? So, this is all very
revolutionary. Uh yes?
>> Yeah, so I'm still a little confused. If
faith is belief without evidence and the
Bible is evidence, then how does
everything work out?
>> Okay.
So, [snorts]
what Don is saying is this, okay?
You have to make sure assumptions about
the world
for your imagination to take root, okay?
For you to reason things out.
If you're always like, "Let's prove God
exists."
Uh or let's
um
uh prove that God has intention, okay?
If you just
um
try to figure out these fundamental
principles, you don't get anywhere. You
can go back and forth.
Okay? But what what I'm saying is like,
let's just assume these things to be
true. Let's just have faith that these
things are true, okay?
Then from these things, you can start
now to use your imagination to work
towards the truth.
Okay? Does that make sense?
Okay? Yes?
>> And because I know the Bible can divide
into two parts. The first part Old
Testament and then the another New
Testament. So, some people believe in
God, some people believe in Jesus. So,
I'm I feel a little bit confused that
what about Dante? Do you think Dante
just believe in Jesus or believe in the
the or God or
>> Okay. So, this is a question, okay? So,
if you actually read the Bible, it's a
complete mess.
Okay?
It's written by like, I don't know, like
100 different people. There are many
contradictions.
And so, what Dante is saying is like,
"Don't read the Bible literally, guys,
okay?
Just read the Bible and see it as a
portal into the mind of God. And what
allows you to enter this portal is your
imagination." Uh yes?
>> Well, at the time, most people didn't
even read the Bible because because of
the it wasn't Latin. So, like
[clears throat] that was at this time,
like it wasn't translated yet.
>> Exactly. Thank you. Yes, okay.
Um
at this time in history, it would
uh be an act of sin to read the Bible by
your by yourself.
Okay? Because
that would only confuse you because
Satan could come into your ear and say,
"Oh, you see blah blah blah." Okay? So,
that's why
um
um you weren't allowed to read the
Bible. So, so, so you have to read at
this time
they didn't really um look at the
contradictions in the Bible. Uh yes?
>> Um so, Dante here uh Dante here, he is
saying a lot of things. He is saying
First, he is comparing faith to a coin.
Second, he's using Saint Peter to
criticize the church that he can
founded. And third, he uh third, he is
saying, "Don't read the Bible too
literally." So, when all these three
things come together, they remind me a
lot of Protestantism. So, is
is uh Dante influenced by uh various
heretical movements, or has he inspired
these movements, or is it both?
>> Okay, we'll never know, but my argument
in this class is that he inspired
everything, okay? Not just the
Protestant Reformation, but also time of
revolution, the Renaissance,
Enlightenment, modernity itself, Okay?
So so so I mean guys, I this is great,
but let's keep on moving on, okay?
Go.
>> [clears throat]
>> Um
line
112.
>> Yes.
>> Thus done, the high and holy court
resounded throughout its spheres with Te
Deum Laudamus, sung with the melody they
use on high. Then he who had examined
me, that baron who led me on from branch
to branch, so that we now were drawing
close to the last leaves, began again.
That grace which lovingly directs your
mind until this point has taught you how
to find the seemly words for thought, so
that I do approve what you brought
forth, but now you must declare what you
believe and what gave you the faith that
you received.
O holy Father, so who now can see what
you believed with such intensity that to
his tomb you outran younger feet.
I then began, you would have me tell
plainly the form of my unhesitating
faith, and also asked me to declare its
source.
I answer, I believe in one God, sole,
eternal, he who motionless moves all the
heavens with his love and love for him.
For this belief I have not only proofs
both physical and metaphysical. I also
have the truth that here rains down
through Moses and the prophets and the
Psalms and through the Gospels and
through you who wrote words given to you
by the Holy Ghost.
>> So here Peter is asking Dante to declare
his faith. What do you believe about
God, okay? And what Dante says like, I
believe that God is love.
Why is this a problem?
This is what he's he's been saying
throughout the Divine Comedy, right? God
is love.
Why would this be a problem? Yes?
>> Um to me, I think he's making
>> No, no, not to you. I'm saying
historically, would this be a problem?
>> I'm I'm saying that he's assuming about
the nature of God. God has frequently
been shown to be not that loving. For
example, the
the ark and Noah and Jonah
>> no, no, no. I'm saying for the Catholic
Church, why is this heresy to say God is
love? It's heresy. Why?
>> The Catholic Church hates some people
and
>> No, no, yes.
>> Well, for the Catholic Church, Jesus is
God.
>> No.
No, no, no. At this time in history,
what are what are Catholics taught?
God is not love, what is God?
>> Stern father figure who punishes you if
you do bad things.
>> Um, no. Like like what is the official
definition of God at this time in
history by the Catholic Church?
No, no, no, no, no. What is God? Like
like like have you guys not
>> Trinity.
>> Yes, it's Trinity. Do you understand?
Okay? This is heresy. You can't say God
is love. You have to say that God is the
Father, the Holy Spirit, and Jesus. They
are separate and equal and one, okay?
That That is what you must say. It's
called the the Nicene Creed. Do you
understand?
To di- to diverge from the the Nicene
Creed is heresy.
Okay? Can can can we drop the Nicene
Creed, okay? You're not allowed to make
adjustments to it. You're not allowed to
question it. You must be cited, okay?
So, at this when Peter asked him, "What
do you believe?" He should have recited
the Nicene Creed. He didn't do that. He
said, "God is love."
This is heresy.
Okay, just
And and I mean, yes.
>> So, the contention is on uno dio, one
God. That's the that's what's heretical?
>> No, no, no, you know, he's saying God is
love.
>> God is love.
>> Right. You can't do that.
>> Not one God versus
>> Okay, okay, okay. Let's read the Nicene
Creed, okay?
This is like This is what all Catholics
must believe.
Not one word can be different, yes?
>> I believe in one God, the Father
almighty, maker of heaven and earth, of
all things visible and invisible. I
believe in one Lord Jesus Christ, the
only begotten Son of God, born of the
Father before all ages, God from God,
light from light, true God from true
God, begotten, not made, consubstantial
with the Father, through him all things
were made. For us men and for our
salvation, he came down from heaven and
by the Holy Spirit was incarnate of the
Virgin Mary and became man. For our
sake, he was crucified under Pontius
Pilate. He suffered death and was buried
and rose again on the third day in
accordance with the scriptures. He
ascended into heaven and is seated at
the right hand of the Father. He will
come again in glory to judge the living
and the dead and his kingdom will have
no end. I believe in the Holy Spirit,
the Lord, the giver of life, who
proceeds from the Father and the Son,
who with the Father and the Son is
adored and glorified, who has spoken
through the prophets. I believe in one
holy, Catholic and apostolic church. I
confess one baptism for the forgiveness
of sins and I look forward to the
resurrection of the dead and the life of
the world to come. Amen.
>> Um so, yeah, this is the modern version,
okay? Sorry. Uh yeah, don't don't worry
about it. It's like the the the But the
old version is the the Trinity, okay?
Um so, this is a problem. Um
Donny got this wrong. But then what he
does is he makes a subtle adjustment,
okay? You can You can You can continue.
>> Verse 139.
And I believe in three eternal persons
and these I do believe to be one
essence, so single and threefold as to
allow both is and are of this profound
condition of God that I have touched on.
Gospel teaching has often set the
imprint on my mind. This is the origin.
This is the spark then that extends into
a vivid flame and like a star in heaven
glows in me.
>> Okay, so now what Don is like, "Oh, you
know what? It's the Holy Trinity, okay?"
So, this is a paradox. God is love, but
I also believe in the Holy Trinity.
Okay? And this is why Don is such a
genius because given this
um impossible situation, like you must
declare faith in the Holy Trinity, he go
he figures out a way to get out of it
and say that God is love, okay? So, I'm
going to go over the Holy Trinity. It's
very important. All right?
So, at this time in history
I don't know. So, not not this time in
history, but in the early Christianity,
there was a huge debate as to the nature
of Jesus.
Okay?
Um
So, the spectrum was that Jesus was was
a man uh and then there was those who
believed that um
Jesus was a god, okay? Pure god. He's
either pure man or pure god. These were
the two extremes.
And um ultimately, the church settled on
in between. He was both man and god.
And then the next debate is
what's the relationship between Jesus,
the Holy Spirit, and God? Because all
three appear in the Bible, right? So,
are they separate or are they one?
And in this time there were many
different theories to explain what's
going on, okay? And there were three
really popular theories that made sense,
okay? So, let's go over the these three
theories. The first is the theory of
modalism.
What does this mean? It means like
God can take different forms, right? God
can be Jesus, God can be the Holy
Spirit, God can be God. Depends where he
is. Depends on what he want wants to do.
He takes different forms, okay? Makes
sense, right?
Then you have the idea of partialism.
Partialism is that
like in an ocean, you You different
seas, right? Well, God is the unity of
God the Father, Jesus, and the Holy
Spirit. And so, they just split off and
do their own thing now and then, okay?
Partialism all makes sense.
And then, you had something called
Arianism. An Aryan was um a
Christian theologian. He argued that
Jesus is a lower God, okay? God created
the universe, and then God created
Jesus. And it's okay to worship Jesus
because Jesus is the one who died for
our sins, okay? So, all three make
sense.
And all three were rejected by the
church.
Okay? In favor
of the Holy Trinity. The Holy Trinity
states
that
Okay.
Okay, all right. States, and this is
really really important, guys, that God
>> [clears throat]
>> um Jesus and the Holy Spirit
are separate
but the same.
And you're like, "Okay, I understood
Modalism, I understood Partialism, I
understood Arianism. I don't understand
the Holy Trinity. It makes no logical
sense."
So, here's the question.
Why would the Catholic Church insist the
Holy Trinity to be the official
doctrine? In fact, they created
something called the Nicene Creed to
enforce this on every single Christian.
If you did not obey, they would come and
kill you. Okay, that's literally what
happened.
So, so, so what what Why
uh yes?
>> Because they wanted to be special and to
prosecute people.
>> Okay. What what's what's the logic?
>> Um
because the entire scripture
concluded or leads to this conclusion,
which it's hard to explain like
logically, but it kind of
if this doesn't like if the Holy Trinity
is not true, then the whole Bible like
description of God cannot um yeah.
>> Okay, all right, all right. So, so the
word is mystery, okay?
Okay? The what the Holy Holy Trinity
does is create the idea of mystery,
which is like God is not knowable. It
you must use faith to accept God. You
understand? That's the reason. The idea
of mystery. Uh yes.
>> It's a litmus test, right?
With the mystery, it's a litmus test.
Are you in my group or
>> Yes, okay.
It's a faith test of faith. Do you
understand?
Okay, the the thing creates something
that you cannot logically explain. The
Holy Trinity is something that you
cannot figure out mentally, okay? It
makes no sense, but you must accept it,
okay? It creates faith, it creates
mystery, and mystery is the foundation
of Catholic Church, right? That's why
there has to be Catholic Church, because
otherwise, you could just do you could
just figure out the word by yourself.
You could just go talk to God by
yourself. But because of mystery, God uh
the Catholic Church must be the shepherd
to lead the flock to God. Does that make
sense? That's why the Holy Trinity is
crucial.
Um but for Dante,
he's not happy about this, right?
Okay?
Why is he not happy?
Because as a humanist, as someone who
believes in human in in the human
imagination,
he's okay with modalism, partialism, and
Arianism, not only because it's
something that we can all understand,
but it's also a story and we can all
partake in, right? You can meet Jesus
and talk to Jesus in modalism,
partialism, and Arianism, but guess
what, guys?
In no situation can you write a story
where you meet the Holy Trinity,
right?
You are
denied access to God.
Does that make sense to you?
Okay? Try try it. Try to write a story
where where you meet the Holy Trinity.
You get nowhere. Okay?
All right? Okay.
So,
how does
Dante resolve this contradiction? He
says that God is love and he believes in
the Holy Trinity.
And this is what makes him genius, yes?
>> He said both is and are, I guess. So, he
kind of admits it.
In his verse 142.
>> I I Okay. Okay. Let's look at 139 and
140, okay? I believe in three eternal
persons, the Holy Trinity, and these I
believe to be of what to be one essence.
What is it one essence?
>> Love.
>> Love. Do you understand? Okay, he's
like, "Listen, we can reduce this Holy
Trinity even further, right?" God is
love.
Jesus is love.
Holy Spirit is love.
God is love.
Okay? This is why Dante is such a
genius, because he takes an impossible
situation, right? Holy Trinity. It's
meant to create mystery, and he and he
solves the mystery for you.
The essence of everything is love.
Yes?
>> So, what is Dante's stance on
ineffability? As in the idea that you
cannot predict or you cannot control you
cannot predict what God will do. You
cannot predict God's nature. What is his
stance on this?
>> No. No. No. No. He's clearly against
this, right? He clearly believes that
you have to have a connection to God.
That's where your intuition and
imagination come from.
Right?
All right? Okay. Does it make sense to
you guys what what he's doing here?
Okay? This is heresy. Like, if they
actually understood the Catholic Church
actually understood what Dante was
doing, they'd burn him at the stake.
But, he uses their language. He makes
subtle changes.
Okay?
You understand?
Okay. Uh yes?
>> So, by defining God as love, is he
setting certain guidelines and
constraints for God's behavior and
motives and personality?
>> Um
what he's saying is that God is perfect.
And so, God loves you unconditionally.
There's nothing you can do to anger him.
There's nothing you can do
to
um make him hate you. He will love you
forever.
Okay?
Uh yeah, yes?
>> I just have one question um about like
why did um
if Prot- Protestantism
is like from directed from Dante, then
why did they also take in the Holy
Spirit as like because like Protestants
still believe in the Holy Spirit, right?
So, why did they still
even though Dante is like just says God
is love, why why why do they still
believe in the Holy Spirit?
>> Um
um
so, this is a really complicated
question,
but Protestantism really is a rebellion
of local princes against authority of
Catholic Church.
Okay? Do you Do you understand? The The
idea of the Holy Holy Trinity is useful
in that it creates obedience to
authority because because of mystery,
right?
So, Protestantism was not people trying
to um promote Dante.
Uh Protestantism was basically a
fracturing
of
um
the geopolitical situation in Europe.
Okay? Does that make sense?
>> But, they were still inspired by Dante,
you see?
>> Um
it's
but they didn't know they were inspired
by Dante.
Okay?
Right? Influence is something you don't
really see.
Uh you you can you can logically uh
yes did did you have a
>> Uh Protestantism is more like a
rebellion against like the political
institution of the Catholic Church. It's
not about like the theology of the
Catholic Church. Well, some part of the
theology, but the Trinity part is
intact. So, it like uh Martin Luther was
okay with Trinity.
>> All right, so so Protestantism, the idea
behind Protestantism, okay, there's like
10,000 different groups, right? But, the
idea is you have a direct connection to
God for the Bible. That's the main idea.
Whereas, Catholic Church is like, "No,
you have to go through us. You can't
read the
Bible by yourself because Satan is in
you. He'll he'll just screw you up,
okay?"
All right. Uh yes?
>> Uh so, I was wondering uh if Donte's
tried to open a new channel to all the
people because people do not need to
just by Bible, but can by love because
love if love is Jesus is God and maybe
people will they all have love, so love
can be the another channel, not only the
Bible.
>> Uh love is what allows you to connect
directly to to God. Uh Peter?
>> Um we have first uh comments online. So,
uh the interesting part of about the
concept of God is that if all things
come from God and nothing exist but
through the Father, then God is both
love and hate simultaneously.
>> Um that's an interesting comment, okay?
So, um
Okay, so the conception of God is that
God is both
eternal
and infinite.
Okay, does that make sense? So, God is a
source of everything and God encompasses
everything. Okay, so God is both um
becoming
and the source. Both being and becoming.
Okay? So, everything is encompassed in
God. And what this is important for us
is that
this is also a paradox, right? How how
you both being and becoming? And the
the way we resolve this paradox is is to
is to say that humans are part of the of
God itself, right? Because humans are
the ones who are becoming, God is the
being, and humans are within God, which
allows for this
process to happen.
Do you understand? Humans represent
infinity, God represents eternity, but
God will encompass both humans as well.
Okay?
All right, yes?
>> I think
my simple vibration of this is that if
God loves us so much, why did he create
hate in the first place?
>> Do you Yes.
>> So, I heard I don't know if the source
is true, but Einstein used to answer
this question that heat is a thing that
physically fire is a thing that exists,
but cold is not. It's the lack of heat.
So, God is the fire or the light just
goes back to chapter 101 that, you know,
he's light, but the lack of him is
darkness. But darkness is not a a
substantial thing, right? Light is
particle, is ray, but darkness is not.
And so, hate is the the absence of love,
but it's not a thing that exists by its
own. So.
>> Okay. All right, so so so let's
continue, okay? But but this answer This
will be answered to you later on, okay?
Because we we will eventually move to a
place
closer to God, where the angels are. And
the angels aren't capable of hatred.
They're incapable of turning away from
God. And the angels are perfect, and
when we get to that section, you will
understand why hate is necessary.
Okay? All right, so so let let's
continue, all right? Continue please.
>> Verse 148.
Just as the Lord who listens to his
servant's announcements, then as soon as
he's silent, embraces him, both glad
with the good news, so did the apostolic
light at whose command I had replied,
while blessing me and singing, then
encircled me three times. The speech I
spoke had brought him such delight.
>> Okay, so do you understand? Okay, so
he's passed the first test. What is
faith? He's answered faith. Now, the
second test is hope. And this will be
asked by um
James, okay, the apostle. Okay, so let's
go to 25, please.
>> Canto 25.
If it should happen, if this sacred
poem, this work so shared by heaven and
by earth that it has made me lean
through these long years, can never
overcome the cruelty that bars me from
the fair fold where I slept, a lamb
opposed to wolves that war on it, by
then with other voice, with other
fleece, I shall return as poet as and
put on in my baptismal font the laurel
crown.
>> Okay, all right, so again, we have to
remember the image of Dante alone in
exile and isolation writing the Divine
Comedy. And what his hope is is to
return to Florence one day, right? And
then have the Florentines crown him as
the greatest poet ever. It will It won't
happen, but that is his hope. That is
his arrogance.
Okay?
Um and
in his heart he knows it is going to
happen, but he's trying to tell us
that that is his great hope.
All right? And it will happen
eventually.
Yes?
Yeah, well, well, you know, Florence, so
so so tell us Dante in Florence.
>> Like, I mean, yeah, afterwards he was
like they built a statue for him and
every and they accepted him as like an
honorary man or like a like the most
important man from Florence or
something.
>> This is that you have manifestation,
right? Where you have absolutely no
evidence this is going to be true, but
you visualize it so much and God will
hear your your your prayer. So, I mean,
after he died, first of all, he was not
allowed to be buried within Florence
with his ancestors.
And
he And there was even people who wanted
to like dig him up and burn him at the
stake. Okay.
Yes?
>> This is my question. Like, if he wanted
if he visualized if he tried to
materialize this wonderful future for
himself returning to Florence as poet
laureate, then why didn't God grant it
to him? Like, if there's a will, there's
a way, right?
>> But God did.
Go to Florence, man.
Go to Florence. He's buried beside
Michelangelo.
>> While he was alive, I mean.
>> Why does God have to grant you this
thing when you're alive? What what what
matters? Your body or soul? We're
starting today. Dante's is staring at us
from where he is and smiling at what
we're doing.
Right? Isn't that what I mean, who cares
if
during his lifetime he didn't get the
reward. He If you go to Florence, he is
God.
>> I would just like to add to that. So, I
think that when we're reading like the
previous cantos, I think we did touch
upon a point that like God will hear
what you want, but like it might not
always manifest like the way you want it
to be, but it's going to like return to
you in in like, you know, a special way.
So, I think that even though Dante
wasn't able to physically go back while
he was alive, like, you know, um his
reputation and you know, his his
aspirations to be crowned as the
greatest poet did happen. So, that is
also a kind of like manifesting.
>> And also like, you know, if you're Moses
and you've led the your people for 40
years across the desert, you freed them
from the pharaoh, and then you go to
Jerusalem become you they call you king,
would they remember you like they like
remember you today? Would you be the
greatest prophet in Jewish history?
Would you be
uh Moses of today? Probably not, right?
If you were a Jesus and you were put on
trial by the Pharisees and the Pharisees
like, "Oops, we'll let you we'll let you
go and we won't crucify you."
Prophets have to be persecuted.
All right?
I'm sorry if you don't like that. Okay,
don't be a prophet then. But prophets
have to be persecuted and that's what
Donna is saying, "I will be persecuted
and this is my hope. I know I'll be
persecuted and I accept it because it is
God's will and it
uh it is God's love for me, okay?"
>> So, I'm really confused as to what he is
encouraging here. So, so he is saying
that, "Oh, okay. I am persecuted when
I'm alive, but I will get rewards when I
die." And he's also saying, "Okay, you
guys persecute me while I'm alive. So,
you guys will burn in hell once you
die." So, what he is saying is that he's
delaying the consequences of these
horrible actions of what happened to him
to the afterlife so that he wouldn't
have to act on them, he wouldn't have to
act against them while he is alive.
>> Okay. What he's saying, okay, it's very
clear, okay? Do not
plan on rewards.
Do not think of the end result. Just act
with
faith,
love,
and hope. Just do that.
Okay? Don't worry about anything else.
You can have these dreams. God may or
may not grant you your dreams. It
doesn't matter. What matters is you live
a life
of faith, hope, and love and that is the
most meaningful, purposeful, and happy
life you could possibly live. Okay? Do
not ever try to say, "If I do this, then
I will, you know, get in Yale and be a
lawyer and be a millionaire and and and
a must." Okay? That gets you nowhere.
Yes?
>> Well, but he did say that he he did
think of the like the end because he
said, you know, he he shall return as a
poet.
>> That is his hope, but he has absolutely
no
evidence that this is going to work out.
>> Yeah.
But he Yeah, okay.
>> Right.
>> Okay? So so so so you're right in that,
you know, like it is believed that if
you truly live a life of faith, hope,
and love, things will work out.
Okay? And the greater your commitment to
faith, love, and hope, the more likely
God is to reward you.
>> But just not in this world.
>> Maybe not in this world.
>> Yeah.
>> All right?
And and and and and that's just that's
just unfortunate. All right, yes?
>> It seems like a really passive way to
act for me. Like somehow it is
>> That this is passive?
>> Yes, this is passive because
>> To live every life, to live every single
day, to live every single moment with
with faith, love, and
>> Yes, yes, you keep
>> and hope. That's passive?
>> You keep saying these words, but these
words do not get you to your goal. You
can live with faith, love, and hope,
then that is great for your spiritual
health. However, it will not get you
back into Florence.
>> The guy is working his ass off every
single day.
>> And he's working not towards getting
himself back into Florence. He's working
towards his faith, hope, and love.
>> Right. And that's what he should be
doing.
>> Okay, then I guess he should make peace
with the fact that he's not in Florence.
Okay.
>> Well, he's definitely made peace because
he's written the Divine Comedy, okay?
Uh yes?
>> I I also feel confused because if the
faith, hope, love is what Dante believed
in, so it's also be contradictory
because then you said uh you don't need
to be rewarded, but actually if you
really believe in love, uh believe in
God, and the God will reward you with
the faith, hope, and love, then this is
reward. So,
you know what I mean?
>> Right right, but but but what we're
trying to distinguish between material
reward and spiritual reward, okay?
Material reward is something you can
see, something you can touch. Spiritual
reward is something that you have you
have to have faith in.
>> Oh, yeah.
>> Okay? All right. Okay, let let let let
let's continue.
>> Verse 10.
For there I first found entry to that
faith which makes souls welcome unto
God. And then for that faith Peter
garlanded my brow.
Then did a light move toward us from
that sphere from which emerged the
first, the dear, the rare of those whom
Christ had left to be his vicars. And
full of happiness my lady said to me,
"Look, look and see the baron whom below
on earth they visit in Galicia.
As when a dove alights near its
companion and each unto the other
murmuring and circling offers its
affection, so did I see both those great
and glorious princes give greeting to
each other praising the banquet that is
offered them on high. But when their
salutations
were complete, each stopped in silence
coram me and each was so aflame my
vision felt defeat. Then Beatrice said
smiling, "Famous life by whom the
generosity of of our basilica has been
described, do let matters of hope
re-echo at this height. You can, for
every time that Jesus favored you three
above the rest, you are the figure of
hope. Lift up your head and be assured
whatever comes here from the mortal
world has to be ripened in our radiance.
The second fire
offered me this comfort at which my eyes
were lifted to the mountains whose
weight of light before had kept me bent.
Because our emperor out of his grace has
willed that you before your death may
face his nobles in the inmost of his
halls so that when you have seen this
court in truth hope, which below spurs
love of the true good, and you and
others may be comforted.
Do tell what hope is. Tell how it has
blossomed within your mind and from what
source it came to you.
>> Okay. Okay, stop. Okay, all right. So,
this is James and he's going to
interrogate
Dante, right? And what the first thing
that thought that James says to Dante
is, "You're special. You were picked by
God to come to heaven before your death
and you have a body." Okay? So, you're
still a human. You're not a spirit. So,
you've been picked out, all right? So,
I'm going to ask you three questions
now. Tell me, what is hope?
Then,
tell me uh what is your hope? And then
the third thing is
where does your hope come from? Okay, so
these are three questions that Dante is
being asked by James. And then something
weird happens, okay? This is a test for
Dante, but what's going to happen now is
that Beatrice is going to come in,
intervene, and answer the second
question, "What is your hope?"
Okay? This is a paradox. Okay,
let's continue to read.
>> So, did the second flame continue? Verse
3 49.
And she, compassionate, who was the
guide who led my feathered wings to such
high flight, did thus anticipate my own
reply. There's no child of the church
militant who has more hope than he has,
as is written within the sun whose rays
reach all our ranks. Thus, it is granted
him to come from Egypt into Jerusalem
that he have vision of it before his
term of warring ends. The other two
points of your question, which were not
asked so that you may know, but that he
may report how much you prize this
virtue, I leave to him.
>> Okay, stop. Okay, all right. Okay. This
is just the arrogance of Dante, okay?
Beatrice comes in and tells
um
James and the entire heavens, and
Beatrice is
perfect, right? So, I think she says
must be true.
She says,
"There is no greater Christian than
Dante." Okay?
Dante.
And he, like Moses, has journeyed from
Egypt into Jerusalem.
He came from exile into the promised
land.
And what is his hope? His hope is to, of
course, write The Divine Comedy. It
doesn't make sense, guys.
Okay?
The Divine Comedy is something that is
sanctioned by God, by the heavens. And
he has been brought into heaven so that
he may find inspiration and the truth to
write The Divine Comedy. This is pure
arrogance.
Right?
And this is what allows him to finish
The Divine Comedy
before he dies. This is what allows him
to for the next few cantos write the
most spectacular poetry ever in human
history, okay? It's shocking what he
will do. Keep on going.
>> Verse 59 to 60. "But that he may report
how much you prize this virtue, I leave
to him. He will not find them hard or
cause for arrogance, as you have asked.
Let him reply, and God's grace help his
task. As a disciple answering his
master, prepared and willing in what he
knows well, that his proficiency may be
revealed, I said, 'Hope is the certain
expectation of future glory. It is the
result of God's grace and of merit we
have earned.'"
>> Okay, stop. Why would this be heretical,
this idea of hope? Hope is the
expectation of future glory. It is the
result of God's grace and of merit we
have earned.
Why would this at this time in history
be controversial?
It's certainly not controversial to us,
but it was controversial back then. Why?
Yes?
>> Well, because
um hope couldn't really exist.
Or like because just the Catholic Church
was the one who issued who went to
heaven or not, and they did that by how
good of the work you did. And so there
wasn't I mean I guess there was some
hope, but like
you didn't have any like sayings.
>> Exactly, okay? That your merit doesn't
matter. It's God's grace that matters.
That's why humility is important, right?
Be humble before God, because you what
if anything you do doesn't matter. It's
God's grace that matters.
Right? And now what Don is saying no is
like merit does matter, okay? So it's an
act of arrogance. Be arrogant. Don't be
humble.
And again, it is very subtle, but that's
what he's saying here. If you truly want
to ascend to heaven, if you truly want
to achieve what you want, you need God's
grace, but you also need to have talent.
You also need to have to work hard.
Okay?
All right. Uh let's keep on going.
>> Verse 70.
This light has come to me from many
stars, but he who first instilled it in
my heart was the chief singer of the
sovereign guide.
>> Do you guys know who the chief singer of
the sovereign guide is?
King David, right?
Okay? King David. And why is King David
so
um important in the Bible? Do do do do
you guys know know the the old Bible?
What Yes?
>> Because he was the man after God's own
heart.
>> Exactly. He He is the person that God
loves the most. There is no other person
that God loves as much as David. Okay,
it's explicit in the Bible. All right,
keep on going.
>> 73 May those, he says within his deity,
who know your name put hope in you. And
if one has my faith, can he not know
God's name?
And just as he instilled, you then
instilled with your epistle, so that I
am full and rain again your rain on
other souls.
While I was speaking in the living heart
of that soul flame, there came a
trembling flash, sudden, repeated, just
as lightning cracks.
Then it breathed forth the love with
which I still burn for the virtue that
was mine until the palm and my departure
from the field would have me breathe
again to you who take such joy and hope,
and I should welcome words that tell
what hope has promised unto me, unto
you.
And I, the new and ancient scriptures,
set the mark for souls whom God Friends,
for me that mark means what is promised
us by hope. Isaiah says that all of the
elect shall wear a double garment in
their land, and their land is the sweet
life of the blessed.
And where your brother treats of those
white robes, he has, with words direct
and evident, made clear to us Isaiah's
revelation.
At first, as soon as I had finished
speaking,
Sperandei was heard above us, all the
circling garlands answering at this
call.
And then, among those souls, one light
became so bright that if the crab had
one such crystal, winter would have a
month of one long day.
>> Okay, so Isaiah is a prophet
who was persecuted.
And what Isaiah says is that all
prophets will be persecuted, okay? All
right, I keep on going.
>> Verse 103
And as a happy maiden rises and enters
the dance to honor the new bride, and
not through vanity or other failing, so
did I see that splendor brightening
approach those two flames dancing in a
ring to music suited to their burning
love. And there it joined the singing
and the circling on which my lady kept
her eyes intent, just like a bride,
silent and motionless.
This soul is he who lay upon the breast
of Christ our pelican, and he was asked
from on the cross to serve in the great
task. So spoke my lady, but her gaze was
not to be diverted from its
steadfastness, not after or before her
words were said, even as he who squints
and strains to see the sun somewhat
eclipsed, and as he tries to see becomes
sightless, just so did I in my attempt
to watch the latest flame. Until these
words were said, "Why do you daze
yourself to see what here can have no
place? On earth
>> So so again, Beatrice intervenes on
Dante's behalf and says, "This soul,
Dante,
uh he has been asked
from the cross to serve in the great
task, okay? So not only is Dante being
compared to
uh Moses, Jesus Jesus uh Moses and
David, he's also also being compared to
Jesus, okay? This is just pure arrogance
on his part.
But it's again his arrogance that will
drive him to greatness. Keep on going.
>> Verse 124
On earth my body now is earth and shall
be together with the rest until our
number equals the eternal purpose.
Only those two lights that ascended wear
their double garment in this blessed
cloister, and carry this report back to
your world."
>> Okay. All right. So um
the reference is this. James
um there's a theory in among theologians
that James was able to ascend to heaven
in his body, okay? And what James is
saying is like, "No, that's incorrect.
Only two individuals in history have
been able to ascend
to heaven with their bodies and that is
Jesus and Mary."
Can someone tell me what what what the
idea here is? Why is it important to to
be able to ascend to heaven with your
body? Yes?
>> To ascend to heaven with your body means
that you're not quite dead by the time
you ascend to heaven. It also means that
you're so good that all the base things
in your body, like your base desires,
your base matter, can be elevated and
can be brought into heaven as it is.
>> Right. Okay. And also judgement day,
right?
>> Yeah.
>> On judgement day, we will all our our
bodies will return to us, okay? All
right. So, in other words, they've
already been judged and they've been
Okay?
Again, this is such an arrogant
statement. Why is this arrogant?
Dante is also able to ascend to heaven
in his body, okay?
Right? Think of the arrogance of this.
Only
James is like, "I'm not even worthy of
ascending to heaven with my body, but
Dante is, okay?"
All right, this is pure arrogance. Uh
I can keep on going.
>> Verse 130.
When he began to speak, the flaming
circle had stopped its dance. So, too,
its song had ceased, that gentle
mingling of their threefold breath, even
as when, avoiding danger or simply to
rest, the oars that strike the water
together halt when rowers hear a
whistle.
Ah, how disturbed I was within my mind
when I turned around to look at
Beatrice, and finding that I could not
see, though I was close to her and in
the world of gladness.
>> Okay, okay. So, again, this idea of
hope. And so, what most people believe
is that
um we as humans should strive to be
egoless, right? To
defeat our ego and learn humility.
And that's what will allow for the grace
of God. What Dante is saying is, "No.
What we must do is turn our ego
for good. To be
to be arrogant in a way, I should
believe that we can
change the world for the better, and we
can make it happen."
Okay? Do you see the difference?
This is arrogant, but it is a selfless
arrogance driven by the ego.
It
All right?
All right, let's move on.
All right, yes.
>> Do you think this kind of mindset is
also in those big tech CEOs and
politicians' minds that they actually
are doing something that they turn their
ego into some big selfless act that
change the world for the better?
>> Right, you're absolutely right, you
know, because everyone believes this,
right? Um so, what's the difference
between them and Dante?
Okay, well, the answer is
faith,
hope, and love.
Right?
>> So, so you mean
those
politicians, the tech CEOs, they don't
have these faith, hope, and love, or
like and why they doing good things?
>> Dante is coming from a very spiritual
perspective, just like Confucius or
Buddha is. So, he's like, "I don't want
worldly earthly reward or fame or
anything." Well, maybe a bit of fame
later on after he died, but like most of
it, it's like spiritual accomplishments.
But for our politicians or
entrepreneurs, they still get, you know,
stock market shares
as a return. So, it's a bit different.
>> Okay. So, the major difference is are
you turning towards God or you turning
away from God? Okay? And the key
variable is love.
And what is love? Love is your
connection to others.
Right? So, are you making others more
capable of love?
Or are you taking away people's capacity
to love?
Uh yes?
>> Um I have like an unrelated question,
but like in the last sentence, the word
gladness, I think that it actually
appears in many cantos, but we haven't
really delved into like the Dante's
definition of this. So
>> Happiness.
>> Just pure happiness or is it like
fulfillment or like
>> Happiness is your connection to God.
>> Okay.
>> Right. The closer your connection to
God, the more glad you are.
>> But does it also have like
uh maybe fulfillment or serenity like in
the word?
>> All right. So, so this is a really good
question, okay? So, gladness is
happiness. Happiness comes from your
connection to God. And what's really
important, okay? And this And this ties
back to your question is
the more
you're able to help others connect to
God, the more happiness is created in
this world. Do you understand? So, your
mission is to be help others connect to
God. That's why the Divine Comedy is a
selfless act because by reading Divine
Comedy, it helps us better connect to
God.
Right? And that's why
uh artificial intelligence is evil
because it's disrupting our connection
to God and focusing our attention to the
material, right? It is making us
helpless.
Right? It's like AI knows knows more
than you, to just believe AI.
Yes?
>> So, I I don't really get. So, like uh
you said that happiness is our
connection to God. And that to
strengthen our connection to God, we
have to create as much as hap- as much
happiness as possible in others. So, if
we're creating this happiness in others,
like Dante is, and we're sacrificing
ourselves in in this life, and we're not
happy, then
is our connection to God really faint
because we're not happy?
>> Uh yes.
>> Your connection to God is not measured
by your happiness, it's by your faith or
your devotion to God.
>> Uh and most of the time it can like if
you're really connected to God and doing
things for him, he'll give you this
internal satisfaction or happiness
because you feel like you're in the
right path or the right way.
>> Right. Again, like stop focusing on the
reward and focus more on the process,
right? How should you live your your
day? And the answer is live every single
day with faith, hope, and love, okay?
Faith is imagination, right? Use your
brain. Use your imagination. Visualize
things. Hope is arrogance. Believe you
matter, believe you can change the
world, and visualize a better world. And
then love is your connection to others.
Act as to help others. Be
Be kind. Be generous, okay?
All right. Okay, let's let's let's let's
let's continue.
This is 26, right?
>> Canto 26.
While I with blinded eyes was
apprehensive from that bright flame
which had consumed my vision, there
breathed a voice that centered my
attention saying, "Until you have
retrieved the power of sight which you
consumed in me, it would be best to
compensate by colloquy.
Then do begin, declare the aim on which
your soul is set, and be assured of
this, your vision, though confounded, is
not dead. Because the woman who conducts
you through this godly region has within
her gaze that force the hand of Ananias
had.
>> Okay, okay, so this is a really
important idea where heaven is so bright
that Dante's being slowly blinded,
right? And if you're being blinded, how
can you now see?
Your eyes don't really work, so how can
you see now? Uh yes?
>> Imagination.
>> Exactly, okay? So now you're forced to
use your imagination, okay? You're
forced to see with your third eye, okay?
Uh
let's keep on going.
Did you have a question?
>> Um I'm saying that this is also like
Um I think it's really funny because
it's actually also a physical
manifestation of blind faith, but I
think in the context of Dante is more
about It's like one of these team
exercises where they put a blindfold
over your head and then push you
backwards and you have to expect not to
fall. Uh it's like a trust exercise.
>> Yeah.
>> No, I think this is like a reference to
when Moses went to the mount to get the
tabernacle, he was blinded by the sight
of God and couldn't see, so that God
gave it him like rocks, um
the 10 Commandments written in stone.
And so I think this is like a reference
>> yeah, yeah.
You're You're You're You're You're
You're right, yes, okay. Yes. Keep Keep
Keep on going.
>> Verse 13.
I said, "As pleases her, may solace
sooner or later reach these eyes. Her
gaze, when she brought me the fire with
which I always burn, the good with which
this court is satisfied as alpha and
omega of all writings that love has,
loud or low, read out to me."
It was the very voice that had dispelled
the fear I felt at sudden dazzlement
that now with further words made me
concerned to speak again. He said, "You
certainly must sift with a still finer
sieve, must tell who led your bow to aim
at such a target."
And I, by philosophic arguments and by
authority whose source is here, that
love must be imprinted in me for the
good, once it is understood as such and
kindles love, and in accord with more
goodness comes greater love.
And thus the mind of anyone who can
discern the truth on which this proof is
founded must be moved to love more than
it loves all else, that essence which is
preeminent, since any good that lies
outside of it is nothing but a ray
reflected from its radiance. My mind
discerns this truth made plain by him
who demonstrates to me that the first
love of the eternal beings is their
maker. The voice of the true author
states this too, where he tells Moses,
speaking of himself, "I shall show you
all goodness." You reveal this too when
you begin your high evangel, which more
than any other proclamation cries out to
earth the mystery of heaven.
>> Okay, so this is a summarization of what
we've learned, right? God is love. God
implanted himself in us, so we are all
love. We aspire to return to love, and
you do that by loving others. Okay? Does
that make sense? All right, carry on
going.
>> Verse 46. I heard, "Through human
reasonings and through authorities
according with it, you conclude your
highest love is bent on God. But tell me
too if you feel other chords draw you
toward him, so that your voice you voice
aloud all of the teeth by which this
love grips you.
The holy intent of Christ's eagle was
not hidden. I indeed was made aware of
what he would most have my words
declare." Thus I began again. "My
charity results from all those things
whose bite can bring the heart to turn
to God. The world's existence and mine,
the death that he sustained that I might
live, and that which is the hope of all
believers, as it is my hope together
with living knowledge I have spoken of,
these drew me from the sea of twisted
love and set me on the shore of the
right love. Believes and leaving all the
garden of the everlasting gardener, I
love according to the good he gave to
them. As soon as I was still, a song
most sweet resounded through that
heaven, and my lady said with the
others, "Holy, holy, holy."
>> Okay, so the idea is that love is an
action, okay? It is an act of openness,
generosity to others.
And when you do that, you turn the
universe towards God. And you bring more
happiness, you bring more love in the
world.
Okay? And while she's saying this, the
entire heavens are shouting, "Holy,
holy, holy." Okay, I keep on going.
>> Verse 70.
And just as a sharp light will startle
us from sleep because the spirit of
eyesight races to meet the brightness
that proceeds from layer to layer in the
eye, and he who wakens is confused by
what he sees, awaken awakening suddenly,
and knows no thing until his judgment
helps him, even so did Beatrice dispel
with her eyes rays which shone more than
a thousand miles the chaff from my eyes.
I saw better than I had before, and as a
as and as a stupefied, I asked about the
fourth light that I saw among us. My
lady answered, and those raised their
gazes with love for his creator, the
first soul ever created by the primal
force, as does a tree that bends its
crown because of winds that gust, and
then springs up raised by its own
sustaining power, so did I while he was
speaking. I bewildered then restored to
confidence by that desire to speak with
which I was inflamed began. Oh, fruit
that was the only one to be brought
forth already ripe. Oh, ancient father
to whom each bride is as a daughter and
daughter-in-law devoutly as I can, I do
beseech you speak with me. You can see
my wish to hear you sooner, I do not
declare it.
And the primal soul much as an animal
beneath a cover stirs so that its
feelings are made evident when what
enfolds it follows all its movements.
Showed me through that which covered him
with what rejoicing rejoicing he was
coming to delight me.
Then he breathed forth.
Though you do not declare your wish, I
can perceive it better than you can
perceive the things you hold most
certain.
For I can see it in the truthful mirror
that perfectly reflects all else while
no thing can reflect that mirror
perfectly.
You wish to hear how long it is since I
was placed by God in that high garden
where this lady read it read it you to
climb a stair so long and just how long
it pleased my eyes and the true cause of
the great anger and what idiom I used
and shaped.
My son, the cause of my long exile did
not lie within the act of tasting of the
tree but solely in my trespass of the
boundary.
>> Okay. All right, okay. So, here
um Dante has passed the test. Uh he
knows what love is.
And now he's talking to Adam, the first
man.
Okay?
And Adam says to Dante, I know
uh your question is how long did it take
me to come to heaven, right? Because I
had the because I committed the original
sin. I uh
trespassed the boundary. I trespassed
the condition that God gave us. And you
want to know how long did it take take
uh
for God to forgive me and allow me to
ascend to heaven, okay?
Why is this paradoxical? Why is this
heresy?
Yes?
>> There is no like the sense of time in
heaven. So you like you just can't
measure how long did it take.
>> Okay, yeah, that's a good point, but
remember he had he was
exiled from the Garden of Eden.
He had to roam the earth.
Right? So the question is like how long
did he have to roam the earth before God
forgave him and allowed him to ascend to
heaven? All right. But this is But
there's a paradox in all this. What
What's the paradox?
>> I think like in the Bible it says he
lived to 900 years or something.
>> Sure, okay, right? There There's a huge
paradox here. What's the paradox? Yes?
>> So maybe Adam doesn't really deserve
heaven to begin with.
Because you know he ate the fruit and
all and he sinned and there weren't any
priests around back then to save him and
basically he's not all that qualified
for heaven.
>> Like if the original sin could be
forgiven then why did Jesus need to like
die for us?
>> Um
that is a good question. But but there's
an answer to this, which is the problem
isn't the original sin. The problem is
our pride.
And so through you know genetics the the
idea of pride the idea of original sin
the idea of evil
um was transmitted transmitted
transmitted from generation to
generation. And that's why Jesus had to
come in order to redeem us of our evil
to ransom us and back from Satan, okay?
That that's the explanation back here.
But, there's a paradox here where
um Adam is saying
I was punished for my trespass of the
boundary. What's the paradox of this?
>> [snorts]
>> Again, it's very subtle. It's hard to
see.
Right? But, in the Bible, if you read
the Bible, if you if you go to Sunday
school,
what are you taught about the Garden of
Eden and the and the fruit?
>> Um the Garden of Eden is the best garden
the best place that you could ever be,
and the fruit is the best thing you've
ever tasted.
>> Who tasted the fruit? Who broke Who
broke the boundary?
>> Uh
Eve.
>> Eve.
>> What's going on here? It's Eve who
trespassed the boundary, and then she
tricked Adam into eating it, right? And
here you're saying, "No, it's Adam."
This is really straight It's a paradox.
This is saying that it's Adam and not
Eve who was responsible for the original
sin.
This is revolutionary, right?
Let me ask you this question.
What is the status of woman in the
Divine Comedy?
>> They're quite elevated. They're the
spokespersons.
>> Beatrice. Right? Think about this.
In heaven, who teaches Dante? Beatrice.
When when we keep on going,
you will find like the person that is
the most elevated in
heaven is not Jesus. Who is it?
Can you guys guess?
Mary.
This is really strange, okay?
So, not only is Adam taking
responsibility for the original sin,
but Mary is being elevated higher than
Jesus.
What's going on here?
Again, this is revolutionary. This is
this is heresy. All right, why is Dante
doing this?
Yes?
>> Maybe he's telling people to stop
blaming women for everything that
happened to you and start taking
ownership of what you have done.
>> Um okay, sure.
Uh
yes?
you and you.
>> So, I think maybe because love cuz you
know women they just kind of
representative love. So, if love does
exist as God, then the woman should be
the God. Maybe.
>> Women should be God, okay? Yes?
>> Well, I mean,
Adam was created first and Eve was made
out of his flesh, so
I don't know that you could say already
that Eve has like a higher form because
she's made out of flesh and Adam is made
out of
um
like or dust
and
and Adam was created as the first human,
so
he and he was told personally by God
that he should not eat the fruit and Eve
was only told by Adam that she shouldn't
eat the fruit. So, Adam has to take the
responsibility for eating the fruit
because
he
he was like told directly by God.
>> Okay, okay, yeah. So, we're not arguing
about it was Adam's fault or Eve's
fault, okay? We we go on and on about
this. But but like I want to know why
women are being elevated to such a
degree in heaven where Beatrice is the
teacher of Dante. It is Beatrice who who
revealed the truth of the universe to
Dante.
And where Mary is elevated more than
Jesus, why would Dante be doing this?
Yes?
>> And maybe he's using the idea of
maternal love again. Like he thinks
maternal love is the closest thing to
selflessness that God has on this earth.
>> That is true. He definitely thinks very
highly of mothers. Yes?
>> I think uh
>> Yes?
uh for Dante the source of love
was originally
uh his love toward uh Beatrice. So
that's why I think he's uh
Beatrice or the feminine
uh
love uh embodies the
you know, the initiator of his love. So
I think that's why he thinks uh highly
of female.
>> Okay, true.
Okay, that that is that is a motivation.
Okay? But
um
what are some other motivations?
Yes?
>> I'm not I'm not that sure, but at the
time
I don't know how the position of women
was, but maybe in society they typically
weren't the teachers and maybe in the
material world
they weren't uh
so enjoying their lives that much, so
sort of inverted in heaven and they
could be saved.
>> Yes, okay.
>> I'm just guessing, but does this have
something to do with like the Catholic
Church and how they treated women at the
time?
>> okay. So this is a soliloquy. This is a
social critique, right? He's criticizing
directly how women are oppressed in
society by the Catholic Church. Does
that make sense?
And what he's also saying is that if
there is if God is to shine in the
world, if love is what matters, you
can't do that.
There has to be equality between the
sexes. Otherwise, there can be no love
in the world.
If women are being oppressed at home in
society,
then uh this is going to negatively
impact society because the children will
grow up thinking that men are superior
to women.
Okay? If there's If you have If you are
to truly access God,
if if love must come to the world, a
precondition must be equality among the
sexes.
Okay, does that make sense?
Okay? So, it's a very subtle social
critique.
Any questions before we move on?
Yes?
>> Well, but Dante doesn't just like make
women equal. He elevates them even.
Right?
So, like
>> Right. Right. It's an inversion, right?
>> Yeah, it's
>> Right. It's a highlight the inequality
of
of the real world, right?
So, so so So, you're drawing this
contrast. There's this massive
inequality in our world where women are
not are not allowed to teach because
they don't know anything. They're not
even allowed to be educated, really,
right?
And where men are always placed in
higher positions than than women, so
he's going to invert this in order to
show you
uh the
inequality
back in our world. Okay, does that make
sense? It's a contrast.
Uh yes?
>> Um I would just like to draw attention
to all the tree motifs he has been
using. That's all I wanted to say. It's
the tree of life, like obviously.
>> Right. Okay. All right. Yeah, there's
lots of reference to the tree. Okay,
let's keep on going.
>> Verse 118.
During 4,302
returnings of the sun, while I was in
that place from which your lady sent
you, Virgil, I longed for this assembly.
While on Earth, I saw the sun return to
all the lights along its way 930 times.
>> Okay, so what he's saying is that after
I died, I went to Inferno, okay? I went
to hell.
Um and who
saved him from Inferno? Did Did do you
Can you guys guess?
No. No. No. Peter doesn't have the power
to save Adam from from inferno.
Jesus, right? Okay. I can I can go on.
>> Verse 1:24, the tongue I spoke was all
extinct before the men of Nimrod set
their minds upon the unaccomplishable
task. For never has anything produced by
human reason been everlasting. Following
the heavens, men seek the new. They
shift their predilections. That man
should speak at all is nature's act, but
how you speak in those in this tongue or
in that she leaves to you and to your
preference. Before I was sent down to
hell's torments on earth, the highest
good from which derives the joy that now
enfolds me was called I. And then he was
called L. Such change must be. The ways
that mortals take are as the leaves upon
a branch. One comes, another goes. On
that peak rising highest from the sea,
my life, first pure, then tainted,
lasted from the first hour to the hour
that follows on the sixth when the sun
shifts to a new quadrant.
>> Okay. So, there's heresy here. What is
the heresy?
Uh yes?
>> Then he was called I.
>> Yes, that's the heresy. Why why why is
this heresy?
>> Should have been Jesus.
>> Uh
Okay.
Uh right. So,
what the Catholic Church insists on is
the consistency
and the constancy
of
Christianity, right?
It's all consistent. And what Adam is
saying is, no, it's all change. We
change the name of God over time and
that was just a natural process.
It doesn't make sense.
Okay? Because what the Catholic Church
is trying to say is that our faith is
immutable and eternal. What Adam is
saying no guys, that's not how that's
how these things work works, okay? Faith
can be can be changed. What matters is
your connection to the divine.
Does that make sense, guys?
All right. So again,
Donny doesn't care anymore. He is going
all out.
All right. Uh yes?
>> But I wonder if the L refers to like El
Olam or something like which is used to
be a old name of God in the Old
Testament. So he was called Jehovah, he
was called a lot of other different
>> Right, right. Okay. So what you're
referring to is the fact that in Genesis
um what Genesis is doing is combining
four different versions of the Bible.
And we know this because there are two
different names for God in Genesis.
There is
uh Elohim, which means gods really, and
then Yahweh. Okay, so we know that these
are two different writers.
Okay, so they're different names. And so
Donny is just drawing us back to the to
this um simple fact, which is like there
is inconsistency in the Bible itself.
Okay? Uh yes?
>> Uh I wonder if you could talk a little
bit about the line from 126, "For never
has anything produced
by human reason been everlasting." What
he means by that.
>> Let me see.
>> Oh, right. Okay. Okay. So so what he's
saying is this, okay?
Um the universe is eternal. God is
eternal.
Okay? But language
um which is a part of our reason, it is
a limited tool
to express the divine.
And over time, what's going to happen is
that we're going to constantly change
our language, constantly refresh our
language in order to express the divine.
Okay? And the people who will try to
refresh our language in order to express
the divine are the poets, right?
Okay?
And this is a natural process.
So,
don't believe everything in the Bible
because the Bible is not necessarily
divine. The Bible is a expression divine
in order to
accommodate our limited senses.
Does that make sense?
>> Yeah, but could could it also refer to
how
over years
human logic can reasoning can always
change like something for example today
that we think is normal 1,000 years ago
it wasn't and vice versa.
>> Right.
>> Um but the
uh faith, the hope that that is
everlasting.
>> Right. That that that's exactly what
what he's saying, okay? But like but I
but what the point the point I'm trying
to make is that reason is predicated on
language.
You only with language can you reason,
okay? And what poets do is they
constantly refresh our language to allow
for more reason
to take place, okay? So, what Dante is
doing is he's trying to promote the
primacy of poetry
over everything else.
Okay? Language.
Okay? Does that make sense?
All right, let's keep on going, guys.
This is now
Canto 27, okay?
>> Canto 27
Unto the Father, Son, and Holy Ghost,
glory all Paradise began so that the
sweetness of the singing held me rapt.
What I saw seemed to me to be a smile.
The universe had smiled. My rapture had
entered by way of hearing and of sight.
Oh, joy, oh, gladness words can never
speak. Oh, life perfected by both love
and peace. Oh, richness so assured that
knows no longing.
Before my eyes there stood a flame the
four torches and that which had been
first to come began to glow with greater
radiance. And what its image then became
was like what Jupiter's would be if Mars
and he were birds and had exchanged
their plumages.
After the providence that there assigns
to every office its appointed time had
to those holy choirs on every side
commanded silence. I then heard, "If I
change color, do not be amazed for as I
speak you will see change in all these
flames. He who on earth usurps my place,
my place, my place that in the sight of
God's own son is vacant now, has made my
burial ground a sewer of blood, a sewer
of stench so that the perverse one who
fell from heaven here above can find
contentment there below."
>> Okay, all right.
This is Peter, okay? And Peter has come
out and he is making the most radical
the most revolutionary
criticism of the Catholic Church, okay?
So, Peter is saying
"He who on earth usurps my place, my
place, my place that in the sight of
God's own son is vacant now, has made my
burial ground a sewer of blood, a sewer
of stench so that the perverse one who
fell from heaven here above can find
contentment there below." This is
This is kind of crazy, okay? What is he
saying? First of all, what is Where is
his burial ground?
The Vatican, okay? The seat
of the Catholic Church.
That's number one. Number two is
who has usurped his place?
>> Satan.
>> Nope.
The Pope, right? Okay?
Um he's made my burial ground a sewer of
blood, a sewer of stench so that the
perverse one who fell from heaven. Who's
the perverse one from heaven?
>> This one, Satan.
>> He's saying the Vatican is the seat of
Satan.
This is literally what he's saying. The
Vatican is the seat of Satan.
What?
And where's he saying this?
Where's he saying this?
In heaven.
Yes?
>> And you know this is not that much of a
surprise because like in Inferno he
already condemned the Pope to hell when
he dies, so
>> That's Inferno. This is heaven.
What should you be doing in heaven?
>> Praising, being happy.
>> How about forgiving others, right? Isn't
that like the like the main Christian
virtue? Forgive others. Understand
others. Show empathy.
Be merciful.
Peter, who is the first Pope, who is in
heaven, who is beside God, who has all
the eternal rewards that he could ever
wish for,
he just goes on this rant
about the Pope
saying this is a servant of Satan.
What is going on here?
Yes?
>> Yeah, because in the medieval Catholic
Church during the back of that period it
was really chaotic, so maybe he just
want to represent that
out of this guy's is not good.
>> Okay, I understand why he's angry, but
the paradox is
uh wait a minute here. You're in heaven,
you're beside God, God is all loving,
God is all forgiving, all merciful, and
you are cursing
the representative representative of God
on earth.
Okay, this is a paradox.
I have absolutely no idea how this was
able to escape the Catholic Church.
Okay, this is pretty blatant what's
going on. Yes?
>> So I know you won't accept this idea
because you said that Dante is perfect,
but personally I think that's him and
his opinions bleeding through a little.
>> Well, well, well, clearly he does not
like being exiled. Clearly he hates the
Pope, right? This is his vengeance.
But at the same time he's a poet.
At the same time he's trying to speak
the truth. And so again, let us give him
grace. Let us assume that what he's
doing
is to speak for God. Why is he doing
this?
What's the purpose of this paradox?
>> [clears throat]
>> And quite honestly, no one knows. This
this has baffled scholars forever.
Okay, this passage is like, what is
going on here? Was Dante drunk when when
he when he wrote this?
>> I think he he did this maybe just to
give a dramatic effect to his poem. Just
so that this could be a
you know, remember as the shocking
literature that was
>> You're right. This is business, right?
We will forever remember this.
Okay, but at the same time, again,
what Dante's been saying all this time
is that God is all forgiving, all love,
all merciful.
Yet Peter cannot forgive
the Pope. Cannot forgive uh yes?
>> To warn humanity, beware of false gods.
Beware of
um just
>> But everyone knows this, like like like
the the corruption of the church is so
blatant. Everyone knows this, right? The
indulgences are are blatant. Yes?
>> Or is it because he thinks that what the
Catholic Church has done really is the
greatest sin in separating us from the
divine?
>> Yes. Can Can you explain? Can you
elaborate?
>> Throughout what we've read in the Divine
Comedy, the the main belief of Dante is
that we should
as humans we can connect to the divine,
but he sees that the biggest blocker of
this is the Catholic Church. Therefore,
what they are doing now on Earth
is the greatest sin and it can't
be forgiven.
>> Yes. Okay.
Uh yes?
>> So, I think it started in John and then
in Ezekiel and then it goes to the Book
of Revelations where they're talking
about the Antichrist. And the Catholic
Church seems to be more
worried about heretics,
but the Antichrist is going to be
somebody inside the Christian community
who's going to purposefully lead
them away in an opposite direction of
God. Where heretics just have other
ideas of God.
>> Yes, exactly. This is clearly clearly
what
Peter's saying is that the Pope is the
Antichrist.
This is This is blatant, okay? There's
no misinterpreting this, okay? There
just isn't. Uh yes?
>> I mean, there's two factors to this. One
is that God is all loving and all
forgiving, but Peter is not God. Like
they're in heaven, they're very close to
God, but Peter is allowed to sometimes
be a little bit hateful. That's the
first part and the second part is that
Dante is not here to stay. Dante is not
here as a permanent resident of heaven.
Dante is here so that he can take a
message and he's going to go back and
he's going to tell everyone all about
what he saw, what he experienced here.
And Peter is giving him this message so
that he can go back and pass it back.
And Peter is doing it with this in mind.
>> Okay, but but but this creates another
paradox, which is like you're in heaven
and you've been there for thousands of
years and all you've experienced is joy
and happiness
where does this hate come from?
Right? This is pure hatred.
Yes?
>> It comes from the hatred of the
subversion of the joy and happiness that
you've experienced.
>> Yes. Okay. It's
justice, right?
It's it's it's it's like the the thing
is so unjust
that you cannot
rejoice in your own happiness.
Okay, does it make sense, guys?
Okay?
And this this this this is the idea of
Martin Luther Luther King's famous
phrase.
Justice
injustice anywhere is injustice
everywhere.
Okay?
Does that make sense? Injustice anywhere
is injustice everywhere. So, it doesn't
matter if it's happening far away from
you. Even it doesn't matter if it
doesn't impact you.
You must speak out.
Okay? That's what love is. Love is
action.
Love is concern for others in a way that
you must act out.
You must You must speak out.
Okay, that's what true love is.
Does that make sense, guys?
Okay, so great. Uh we'll take a break
for lunch and then we'll come back,
okay? All right. But but you guys are
doing a great job. We're going really
fast. And you know, our mission is to
really reveal Dante's will and testament
to the world and we're doing that right
now, okay? So, thank you very much and
we'll continue after lunch.
Okay, guys. So, uh we continue, okay?
So, again,
um I want to summarize what we've
learned so far
um this morning.
So,
um
for most of its history
Paul was a major theologian
of the Catholic Church. It's Augustine
who
systematized Paul, but it's really Paul
as the heart and soul of the Catholic
Church.
And he basically has three chief
virtues, right? Um
faith,
um hope,
and love.
And if you read his letters,
he will explain to you what these three
things mean.
Faith is just acceptance.
Understand the universe is a mystery.
God works in mysterious ways.
And you have to trust him, okay? You
have to accept him, you have to trust
him.
Hope is humility.
Understand that everything works by the
grace of God. You'll be saved by God.
And you must be humble before the power
and grace of God.
Uh and love is just obedience.
To obey the church,
to obey God, and then the church will
lead you to salvation.
And for again, most of its history, the
church will teach
Paul's understanding, okay?
Um Dante
is a revolutionary. And he will take
these three concepts and radically
reimagine them uh as we discussed this
morning. So,
the for faith, it is not about
acceptance. It is about
um
imagination, right?
We imagine
that we are ultimately connected to God.
And we're connected to each other. It's
an act of imagination. That's what faith
is.
Constant recognition
that the universe is one and whole. And
it is governed by love and free will.
Hope is one of arrogance.
To believe that you yourself can be
Jesus. You can be David. You can be
Moses as long as you have the will to do
so.
Um and through your actions, you can
change
the universe.
Um and then love is one of action.
Right?
It's almost disobedience where if you
see justice anywhere, you recognize
through your faith, through your hope
that you have the power to change it
because justice anywhere is justice
everywhere. That's why Peter is so angry
even though he really has no reason to
be angry. Okay? So,
a way for us to understand the
difference is Paul's saying,
"There is a plan and trust it, okay?
Trust the plan."
What Donny is really saying is that we
are the plan.
We are the ones who bring faith, hope,
and love to the world. That is the plan.
That is why we're here.
And that is And so, this is a brief
summary of thing of things that we
learned this morning. Are there any
questions
about
what we learned this morning before we
continue?
I know we're going very fast.
Uh you guys are doing a great job, but I
want to make sure that you're on track,
that you understand what Donny is really
trying to say. Yes?
>> Um so, what Donny is trying to say he's
not trying to get rid of obedience
entirely. He's He's uh not trying to
push self-determination. He's saying,
"Okay, be obedient, but don't be
obedient to the church. Be obedient to
God and the voice within you." Is that
what he's saying?
>> Okay. What I'm trying to point out is
what the priorities are.
Right?
For Paul, the priority the priority is
to accept the mystery of God, to be
humble with with before God, and to obey
God.
And what Don is saying is that no, we
are not passive
observers. We are active participants in
the universe. And we have a
responsibility
to
uh
use our imagination
to believe we can change the world, to
have courage,
and to love others.
Okay?
To promote justice in the world. It
doesn't It doesn't do you no good if you
live a virtuous life as long as there's
injustice in the world. So, again, every
This all radical.
This all a radical conception
revolutionary conception of our place in
the cosmos.
Okay? And again, it's this
It's these three things. This
imagination, this arrogance, this
um
desire to take action. Okay?
It's the driving force behind modernity,
right? It's what will give rise to
Protestant Reformation,
the Enlightenment, the Renaissance, the
Scientific Revolution. It's these It's
these three ideas.
Right? It's It's this conception that
will change human history forever. I
know it's hard to believe,
but
if you think about it,
okay?
And you just apply it to human history,
it helps explain a lot a lot
rather than just say, "Well, history's
driven by these structural forces that
are materialistic as Marx would argue."
Right?
>> So,
so, history is not driven by these
structural forces that are
materialistic?
>> This
What Don is saying is that history is
determined by the active choices that we
make.
That's what Dante is saying, ultimately.
Okay? We're not just passive observers,
right? Marx would say that
there's these structural economic forces
that drive history, and what Dante is
saying is that no, it's humans that
drive history. It's us.
Yeah?
>> Could Dante's idea of humans drive
history be the root of this
great men great people idea of history
instead of collective history?
>> Um that's a hard question for me to
answer.
Dante is the root of the Renaissance. He
will give rise to the Renaissance. And
the ideas of the Renaissance will
spread. How it spreads, how it interacts
with other ideas is a very complicated
question.
Okay? All right, so
yes?
>> Um so yeah, [clears throat] I was I was
thinking about
an interview of you and some other guy I
I watched and and you said
that individuality and creativity is the
greatest threat to the system and
basically you when you have that
individuality you can deny the reality
before you and create your own reality.
And that kind of
align with what Dante said about the
arrogance as
hope. Do you find personal connection
with Dante in this?
>> Okay, so I'm going to make a very
arrogant statement, okay? So I first
discovered Dante 4 years ago when I was
forced to teach Dante for this great
books course I was teaching in high
school. And before I never read Dante.
Um and I never had a desire to read
Dante.
And it was a very tough journey. And 4
years later I will make the statement
where I feel I understand Dante
better than anyone else in the world.
Okay?
>> [clears throat]
>> This is me not knowing a word of
Italian. This is me not having studied
Dante formally. This is me not knowing
the scholarship behind Dante. Okay? But
I But you could do this as an expert
where you go and try to sit on every
Dante classroom. All right? And I
guarantee you
that
the conclusion that you will make is
I have a better understanding of Dante
than everyone else. Because what I'm
trying to figure out is the psychology
of Dante.
The heart of Dante. The mind of Dante.
And um
I feel as though
when I teach Dante I'm channeling Dante.
I think Dante is looking at us, smiling
at us.
And a lot of things that I say, a lot of
things I do, I'm trying to harmonize
with Dante. I'm trying to open my heart
in a way that allows Dante to take
possession of me and guide me in a
certain way. Okay? It's almost like the
Holy Spirit, right?
All right? So that that's what I
believe. It's kind of crazy
but prove me wrong. All right? Find me
someone who can teach Dante better than
I can.
Yeah?
>> yeah, I'm going to be honest with you. I
think the only thing that Dante scholars
can agree on is that they
they have the best definition and best
understanding of Dante.
>> Okay. Give me an example.
>> Um for example, all these people who
scholarship you just attempted to
refute. For example, the people in the
commento by Bruno Nardi for the type of
the text and translations. Their
interpretation kind of diverges from
yours.
>> Okay. Well, then I I'd be more than
happy for you to read everything they
write and then tell us what they write
and have an argument. Okay? I'm probably
open to that. Just tell us like this
Dante scholar believes this. And And And
And I'd be I would love for this for for
this argument to take place so that
people can hear a diversity of
perspectives, okay? But I'm pretty
confident that my perspective has more
weight.
Okay?
Uh yes?
>> So, I like I like what you said about
individuality cuz I was trying to I was
trying to build it into it. I thought
I'd build it individuality into it
into action cuz it's individual action.
But I The more that I'm looking at this,
maybe instead of Holy Trinity, it's a
mortal trinity or something like that
because individuality seems to be your
individual imagination, your individual
arrogance, your individual action.
So, all three kind of work into the
individual and it's almost like God
would want our individualized love.
>> You're absolutely right. So, Dante, what
he does, that's very controversial, is
he celebrates individuality to an
extreme degree.
What he's What he's saying is like, you
know, he's not saying, "Working
together, we can save the world." He's
saying that one person with enough
faith, hope, and love can change the
entire world. That's arrogance, right?
That's That's a celebration of
individuality that is pretty extreme.
And uh yeah, so thank you for that,
okay? Uh yes?
>> So, um what I'm actually very interested
in is um why um
is there any um personal personal
experiences of yours that help you or
connect with Dante?
>> Yeah, so it's it's has to do with exile.
Right? So,
um
um all my life I've been in exile.
I was an immigrant
to Toronto, where I grew up. Then I went
to Yale,
um which was basically isolation because
I I really didn't fit into the cultural
milieu of Yale. And then from Yale I
went to China where I was looking for my
identity. I was looking for my roots,
but it was I was very much a stranger in
a strange land because as you can see,
my values are very Western, right? And
I'm not going to get along with Chinese
people
because I am very much
anti-materialistic. So, it's this sense
of isolation, this sense of exile that
allows you to connect to a higher truth,
okay? And that's the major connection.
It doesn't make sense?
>> Yes, I think you did.
>> Yeah, but but but but yes.
Uh yes.
>> Um but I would like to point out that
your exile is um
mostly voluntary. I want to say that
>> So, it's voluntary.
>> Um no, it wasn't.
>> Yes, it was.
>> literally forced out of Florence and all
his property was confiscated.
>> Okay, as long as he was willing to admit
his crimes, as long as he was able to
willing to compromise with the new
faction, he would have been allowed to
let in. He made the conscious decision
to leave
Florence, okay? Just go into the
history, okay? Like they made many
overtures to to him and said, "Listen,
let's make a compromise and you'll keep
your property, but you must, you know,
pay a fine or whatever." He thought it
was unjust, okay? So, it's his choice.
Uh yes.
>> Uh first, I have a question. Is that
you're saying that uh your experience
like you have lots of experience about
the exile to different culture and
different countries and you think that I
mean those kind of experience make you
like quite approaching to the truth,
approaching to the free will of of God.
So, does that means like uh if for us
who never have the experience to to
immigrate or like uh being exiled from
group, it's much more harder for us to
approaching to the approach to the God.
So, does that means uh human culture for
the people in the like in a population,
those kind of people in the population
from the culture kind of prevent people
to um
getting the truth from the God?
>> Look, I mean, if you live in a city,
you're going to be much more creative
than if you live in the countryside. If
you are cosmopolitan and you travel to
many countries, you're going to be more
creative than if you are just you just
stay where you are, okay? That's that's
just historically accurate. At the same
time, we need to recognize that Dante
never really traveled that much.
He really was within Italy himself. He
didn't go and learn all the all these
things, okay? So,
there seems to be a balance where if you
stay in one place, you become
complacent, but if you go too far, you
[clears throat] become rootless.
Okay? Because what's driving Dante, we
have to remember this, is his love for
Florence, his love for his family, his
love for his neighbors, for Beatrice.
Okay? So, he's very much rooted in
Florence. He never really leaves
Florence
mentally, psychologically. He may leave
Florence physically, but even when he
leaves Florence, he still remembers
Florence, he still
is nostalgic for or Florence. He still
longs to return to Florence. Okay? Does
that make sense? There has to be a
balance.
Okay. All right.
I Let Let Let us continue, okay?
>> Canto 27, verse 28.
Then I saw all the heaven colored by the
hue that paints the clouds at morning
and evening, with the sun confronting
them.
And like a woman who, although secure in
her own honesty, will pale on even
hearing another woman's failing,
just so did Beatrice change in
appearance. And I believe that such a
close was in the sky when he, the
highest power, suffered.
Then his words followed with a voice so
altered from what it was before, even
his likeness did not display a greater
change than that.
The bride of Christ was never nurtured
by my blood, and blood of Linus and of
Cletus, to be employed in gaining
greater riches,
but to acquire this life of joyousness,
Sixtus and Pius, Urban and Calixtus,
after much lamentation, shed their
blood.
We did not want one portion of Christ's
people to sit at the right side of our
successors, while on the left the other
portion sat.
Nor did we want the keys that were
consigned to me to serve as an
escutcheon on a banner that makes war
against the baptized. Nor did we want my
form upon a seal for trafficking in
lying privileges, for which I often
blush and flash with anger.
From here on high one sees rapacious
wolves clothed in the cloaks of
shepherds.
You, the vengeance of God, oh why do you
still lie concealed?
The Gascons and the Cahorsins, they both
prepare to drink our blood. Oh good
beginning to what a miserable end you
fall.
But that high providence which once
preserved Lucius Scipio, the glory of
the world, for Rome, will soon bring
help, as I can see.
And you, my son, who through your mortal
weight will yet return below, speak
plainly there and do not hide that which
I do not hide.
>> Okay, right. So, um this again is Peter
and he's and he's saying
um
And he he he's saying, "Okay,
that the Vatican is now the seat of
Satan, right? So, what can be done?"
What can be done?
First of all, why didn't God just
intervene?
Why didn't Peter just intervene and kill
Satan or whatever? Yes?
>> Because that would be that is
disrespecting people's free will. If
intervening.
>> Exactly. So, God cannot intervene,
right? Because again, the fundamental
principle of the universe is free will.
And free will is a manifestation and
expression of God's love for us. Okay?
If you truly love, you must
give people choice. Yes?
>> But didn't God intervene multiple times
in the Old Testament?
>> For example?
>> Well, the ark of Noah and
like in the
Noah story.
>> Um
that's not
uh right. And then
and then what did God say to Noah
afterwards?
>> That it was a mistake.
>> Exactly. Do you guys Do you guys
understand? There's something called the
Noahide covenant. So, he told Noah, I
destroyed the world and I shouldn't have
done that, man. [laughter]
Okay? So, God learns, okay?
>> But he still intervened.
>> Excuse me?
>> He still did it.
>> What? And he said, I'm sorry. I won't I
won't do it I won't ever do do it again.
>> So, that's the only instance you see.
What is it? Just That's the only
instance where he intervened.
>> Um well, I mean he's he's Well, in the
Old Testament, he did intervene in quite
a lot, right? But
>> But that's the last one.
>> No, no, no. That That was him just
saying like I won't destroy humanity if
I'm angry.
Okay? Do you understand? He's like, I
will never destroy humanity again.
Uh yes?
>> Um but you said earlier that God was
perfect love. So,
why did he self-admittedly do this?
>> Okay. Um
>> [laughter]
>> Yes.
>> So, um I used to go to a Bible college,
so we have to write a lot of essays
about these contradiction uh dictions in
the Bible, but we can talk about that
after class if you want. Yeah.
>> Okay. Um
so,
we can go on for years about the
contradictions in the Bible, okay? And
what Dante is saying is that let's just
use our imagination, okay? And look
look, there's like 10,000 explanations
and one explanation is it's not really
God that's doing this, it's the demonic
urge that's doing this, which is a false
god, right? So so but but like I don't
want to go there, it's too confusing.
Okay? But like there are many different
explanations for for what happened. All
right? So again, the question is Peter
says there's so much evil in the world.
So what does he tell Dante to do?
What is Don- what must Dante do?
To address the evil in the Catholic
Church.
Write Divine Comedy, right?
Okay? Tell the world. Write Divine
Comedy.
That's why you're here. That's why God
elevated you even in your body.
It doesn't make sense. Okay? Yes?
>> I'm a little bit confused with the line
56 and 7. Um you the vision is of God.
Oh why do you still lie concealed? What
what does that lie concealed
lie concealed mean?
>> Why doesn't God Why why doesn't God take
action?
>> I'm sorry?
>> Why doesn't God take action?
Right? You the vision is of God.
Right? You God, you're being offended by
all this
corruption. So why do you still not do
anything about it?
Why do you not take action? Why do you
lie concealed?
>> So so you asked to
to God, right?
This
>> It's a lament. It's a lament. Yes, it's
you God. Yes, okay. Yes, okay.
>> All right.
Okay? Let let let let let's keep on
going.
>> Verse 67.
As when the horn of heaven's goat abuts
the sun, our sky flakes frozen vapors
downward. So did I see that ether there
adorned, far from that sphere,
triumphant vapors now were flaking up to
the empyrean, returning after dwelling
here with us.
My sight was following their semblances
until the space between us grew so great
as to deny my eyes all farther reach. At
this my lady, see- seeing me set free
from gazing upward, told me, "Let your
eyes look down and see how far you have
revolved."
I saw that from the time when I looked
down before, I had traversed all the arc
from of the first climb, from its
midpoint to end, so that beyond Cadiz I
saw Ulysses Ulysses' mad course, and to
the east could almost see that shoreline
where Europa was sweet burden.
>> Okay. All right. So, Beatrice, they are
really up high, okay? They are so close
to God, okay? Uh they're about to enter
the empyrean, which is the uh seat of
God.
And then Beatrice says, "Look down and
see how far you've risen, okay?" And
he's he's recognized that, "Oh my God,
he's traveling higher length of the
cosmos."
Uh
let me ask you this question.
Why is Beatrice
guiding Dante? Why was Beatrice chosen
to be Dante's guide through the cosmos?
Uh yes?
>> Um personally, I would say that it's
because uh
Beatrice is the person who is familiar
to Dante. And all of this is so grand
and so beautiful and so great that if
Dante tried to take it in himself, or if
he was guided by someone uh who is like
a saint or someone not familiar to him,
then he would have problems taking it
all in. So, this Beatrice is kind of
like a bridge bridge of love between
Dante and God.
>> Then why not why not Dante's mother,
man?
>> Wait, is Dante's mother still alive at
the time of writing?
>> No.
Uh yes.
>> I I think because uh Dante loved
Beatrice.
>> Exactly. You understand. It's that
simple. Because what's elevating you is
your love for another person, okay? And
the love is so powerful, it's almost
like a tractor beam. It's like a rope
that carries you.
Okay, do you understand this idea? Okay,
he's not flying. And what's allowing him
to fly is not Beatrice, it's your love
for Beatrice. So, it has to be someone
that Beatrice loves with all his heart.
And that's why Beatrice was chosen.
And that's how Dante was able to
traverse the cosmos the cosmos. Not him,
not his will,
okay? Not his imagination, but his love
for Beatrice.
That's what did it. Does that make
sense? Okay, this is a very important
distinction.
Okay, let's let's continue.
>> Verse 85.
I should have seen more of this
threshing floor, but for the motion of
the sun beneath my feet, it was a sign
and more way.
My mind, enraptured, always longing for
my lady gallantly, was burning more than
ever for my eyes return to her.
>> Okay, so so you guys know what's going
on. It's like she he is so obsessed with
her, okay? He What's keeping him going
is the sight of her.
Right? That's what gives him faith,
hope, and love. He has to see her. So,
wherever she goes, he wants to go as
well. And it's his love for him
I'm sorry, it's his his love for
Beatrice that propelled her his will and
his imagination. Okay, that's the
dynamic here. And that's the dynamic of
the universe. Uh yes?
>> Um I remember earlier on you mentioned
that for the writer Dante, like Beatrice
is kind of like another reflection, but
a greater self of himself.
>> Yes.
>> And I was wondering, now since we're
analyzing um Dante's love towards
Beatrice,
but since it's also a reflection of
himself, but a greater self,
could this love be more than he wants?
>> This is a great question, okay? So so
let's sit back and and think about this.
Where
to love someone, okay? You have to love
this person unconditionally. So you have
to remove your ego from the equation.
Um but the problem is
Dante didn't know Beatrice,
right? They they knew each other when he
was like eight,
and they knew each other on and off. So
Beatrice is not a fully conceived
person.
Uh yes?
>> So maybe Dante here is preaching a
radical self-love because the church
tells you to feel guilty for all the
sins you have done. Tells you to be
uh
to feel humility in front of the church,
but Dante here is preaching self-love.
Be confident and love yourself.
>> No no, I don't think Dante would do
that. This is He would not preach
narcissism. I have a hard time believing
that.
>> Well, I don't think it's narcissism.
Loving yourself and narcissism is not
the same thing. Narcissism is relating
your ego. Loving yourself is being kind
to yourself.
>> Okay, this is really important because
the reason why I say this is next week
we'll be will we will focus on the
cosmic battle between Virgil and Dante.
Okay? We will focus on the cosmic battle
between the Virgil and [clears throat]
Dante. It's very important we
distinguish clearly what is true love.
And when we learn about Virgil, you will
recognize that
uh there is a narcissism to his concept
of love that does not exist in Dante.
Dante's love is unconditional.
Okay? Uh yes?
>> Uh
So in the City of God, which I'm I'm
kind of digging into now,
um
Jesus dies as a sacrifice for our sins
and and Augustine wants us to mirror his
his sacrifice and his suffering. And so
I think maybe what what they're asking
for is instead of like radical self-love
or love of any one thing it'd be
the love of the acceptance of this
sacrifice and the suffering in this
life.
Um
of Jesus.
>> Right. Okay, so yeah, so Dante would
demand that you leave your ego, that you
transcend your ego, okay? Doesn't mean
you abandon your ego. Your ego uh is
very important,
but you have to
reach out to someone else. So So again,
it's a really interesting question to
think about.
Um
what's going on here?
Dante and Beatrice died when she was
like 24, 25, okay?
And Dante got married.
He married someone, okay, who was not
Beatrice.
Beatrice married someone else, um and
she died actually in childbirth.
Um and
so
Beatrice is not a fully conceived
person. So, what's going on here?
Yes?
>> Um I think two things are happening.
First thing is that this is a very
contemporary take, but the thing we
cannot get is the most perfect in our
mind. So, because Beatrice is dead, like
Dante's perception of her remains
forever when she was young and when he
was a teen basically a teenager, a young
adult, and he was thinking that she is
all kinds of perfect, and her image is
forever frozen at that age.
>> Is Beatrice a child here?
>> No. No. That's not what I'm saying at
all.
>> Okay.
>> I'm saying that his image of her is
frozen, and that she cannot do anything
to upset it.
>> No. No. No. No. No. No. Yeah.
>> So, I uh you know, since we have a
Italian uh scholar already, so I'm going
back to text for list and original list
analysis. Beatrice means uh the uh
you know uh the blessed.
>> The blessed, yes.
>> So, maybe uh this whole uh figure in in
in in this work is not a real person at
all. It's just a you know, a literary
>> I disagree. No.
>> construct.
>> No, no. If If she were not a real
person, if she was just a figment of
Dante's imagination, the Divine Comedy
would not work.
It could not hold together.
It The Divine Comedy has to be an act of
love, okay? She just has to be a real
person, yes?
>> Yeah. Well, I I have a question because
I think Dante did believe in love, but
if he you don't believe we'll fall in
love with someone,
and you just get married, then you say
you believe in love. So, I think it's a
bit contradictory.
>> Okay. All right. Okay. Okay. Okay. Look,
look, we're out of time, okay? So, so
I'll I'll I'll tell you my
interpretation, okay?
Dante
could not have known Beatrice the
person,
but he could have known Beatrice the
soul.
Do you understand this?
Even though she's dead,
he could still, with his imagination,
with his will, with his love,
he could still communicate with
Beatrice.
Okay?
And how we know this is
all the poetry that Dante wrote about
Beatrice before the Divine Comedy.
Right? So, Beatrice was his muse
throughout his life. Even though he
married someone else, even though
Beatrice is dead. This is a really hard
thing for you guys to appreciate, okay?
But when you have an imagination, this
imagination works by connecting to the
entire cosmos. You're able to focus your
imagination in a certain way, you're
able to talk to the person that you most
love.
Okay?
Does that make sense?
Okay. Does that make sense to you? So so
I I'm not saying this this is what
happened, I'm saying this this is a
resolution to that paradox here. How is
it that Dante doesn't know Beatrice as a
person? Well, the answer is he knows
Beatrice as a soul.
Okay?
His mind was able to lift up to heaven
um and communicate with Beatrice
throughout his life.
And then the question is like, how was
he able to do this? And the answer is
they were soulmates, okay? They were
born and they were meant to be together,
but because of fate they had to
separate.
But their souls were still aligned
together in the cosmos.
All right, yes?
>> I am reminded of Piccarda and her story.
So like she was in the end forcibly
married to a man, but
to a man and but she said herself that
her heart was still with God and the
fact that she is in heaven right now
proves this. So I wonder if the
situation between Dante and Beatrice
might be more of the same. Even though
Dante is married to another woman, his
heart will always be with Beatrice.
>> Okay. This This is a really hard
question to answer, okay?
And again, we're just going to use our
imagination.
God is the source.
We we we long to return to God.
Okay?
A soulmate is different. A soulmate is
connection between two
two
sparks, right? Two lights
that communicate with each other and
which allows you to draw closer to God
together. Does that make sense?
This is a very important distinction
because Dante will say this and this
this is a very important distinction
between Dante and Virgil. Dante says you
you can only love someone else. You can
only love a person. You can't love God.
You can't love a concept. You can't love
money.
You can only love another person. If
that were not the case, love has no
meaning, okay? Whereas Virgil is like,
"Yes, you can. You can love God. You can
love this. You can love that, okay?"
Again, when we when we get to Virgil, we
are going to really appreciate this.
Uh
Can we move on? Okay, please. I mean,
it's it's
Okay. So, first of all, um we have a
friend. Uh could you introduce her, uh
Carol?
>> I'm delighted to introduce Aurelia, who
is a much more recent Yale College
graduate than Jon or I, um and is now
studying at Yenching Academy, and she
has kindly um made herself available to
come read um the Italian portion for us
today.
>> And and you've read Dante before?
>> Yeah.
>> Okay, good. Okay. All right.
>> But only Inferno.
>> Oh, okay. All right. Okay, so this is
Paradise. We are now in Paradise. Why is
it you guys spend all your time in hell?
Like
Seriously.
>> Hell is so interesting. I mean, there's
so many terrible punishments. It's kind
of fun to read about them.
>> All right. All right.
Okay, well, thanks so much for coming.
And so, what we're going to do is uh
maybe you'll read a tercet.
And then you'll read the tercet, okay?
And and and and and then and then we'll
go on like that, okay?
And and again,
um
why it's important here here the Italian
is, it's designed to be read and spoken
aloud in Italian, okay? So, you can't
really understand the poetry unless you
hear it um aloud. Okay? And like, not
knowing Italian,
um I'm going to make some stupid guesses
about what's going on, okay?
Um and then feel free to say I'm stupid
or something, okay? All right. Okay. All
right. So, so so let's continue, please.
>> Um
I'll pick up at 88 first, and then we'll
do it one by one.
My mind, enraptured, always longing for
my lady gallantly, was burning more than
ever for my eyes return to her.
>> Oh, wow.
That's beautiful.
Oh, wow. Okay.
This is why Dante is the greatest poet
in the world. You can now hear the
beauty, right?
Wow, okay. Um any comments about it? Can
you Can you do that again? Okay, cuz
it's so beautiful. And can you do it a
bit slower so we can catch the cadence,
the the the the the the sort of
fluctuations in sound?
Oh, wow. Okay.
Wow.
Any any any thoughts, guys?
Any impressions?
>> Uh to be honest, it sounds much more
gentle and it sounds much softer than
the English version. I'm going on vibe
here, but what I'm saying is that
English version does not convey the idea
of love enough. It talks about love, but
it does not make you feel it.
>> Yeah. I felt I felt my soul like
vibrating, okay? And and and No, I'm
serious. And that's what Dante is
saying. The universe is energy, it's
vibration, it's love. And this language,
it is energy, vibration, and and love,
okay? This is why it's important to read
the Italian because when you read the
Italian, it is structured in a way so
that you vibrate with the universe. It
draws you closer to the source. Uh yes?
>> Yeah, I was
I would actually like maybe maybe
whatever to hear more because we don't
even get the opportunity to take
advantage of the
of the end rhyme scheme, the ABA BCB.
>> Yeah.
>> And it it it goes and it it it all be
sing song.
>> Yeah, so that's why people tremble
at Dante because it has to be an angel,
right? When you when you when when he's
be saying this poetry to you, he's like
an angel has taken possession of you and
conveying the beauty of God. How else do
you explain this beauty, right? Okay, so
so so let let us go on with the reading.
>> Verse
oops, sorry.
Verse 91.
And if by means of human flesh or
portraits, nature or art has fashioned
lures to draw the eye so as to grip the
mind, all these
Should we
probably read a little more than a
tercet?
>> Sure sure sure sure. Yeah, let's let's
let let let let
let's just
>> [clears throat]
>> read tercets, okay?
>> Okay.
>> All these would seem nothing if set
beside the godly beauty that shone upon
me when I turned to see the smiling face
of Beatrice. The powers that her gaze
now granted me drew me out of the lovely
nest of Leda and thrust me into heaven's
swiftest sphere. Its parts were all so
equally alive and excellent that I
cannot say which place Beatrice selected
for my entry.
>> And I will appoint out that now we can
connect it together, right? Where I just
told you that Dante could only have
written this
because of his love for Beatrice, right?
And like if you hear the language, you
hear the Italian, it's almost like
they're making love.
It doesn't make sense.
But this just the vibrations is almost
sexual.
>> It's beautiful.
>> Yeah, yes, okay. Like keep on going.
>> I mean, I agree. I feel like there's
something like very like the s-
the s- like there's a kind of like more
uh
what's the word?
>> Sensual.
>> And then also like the s- the uh what I
forgot
English like the s- like the
the sibilance the sibilance like it like
comes through a lot more
>> Right.
>> Yes.
>> Just out of curiosity, how close is this
Italian to exactly
>> It's exact.
He created Italian, okay? This is the
guy who created the modern Italian
language.
Yes.
>> Oh, no, I was just stretching my hands
so
>> Okay, yes. Um so
um
Dante has created this uh long time ago.
I'm wondering if the actual meaning of
the words or the pronunciation have
changed changed since then.
>> Uh I'm guessing not.
Uh my my guess is it hasn't. But but but
you you would know better better than I
do.
>> So it's a different it's different than
modern Italian. Like it sounds more It's
It's It almost sounds like the dialect
that you would find in the south. Like
some of the kind of the ways that some
of the words are shortened into one or
like you can see "Che non so dire." Like
that would be k e o non so dire. So he's
kind of It's It sounds You can
understand it with modern Italian, but
it sounds different. Almost like you'd
read
closer maybe to Shakespearean English.
Kind of that type of feeling.
>> Okay. Yes.
>> How different is it for you from
Inferno?
Reading it.
>> It's like way more I feel like it's way
more transcendent and beautiful.
>> Yeah, great question. Okay. So So what I
My guess, okay, I don't know, okay, but
my guess is that
Dante is trying to mirror the vibrate
vibration of the universe, okay? So
obviously in heaven vibrations are
higher.
Okay. Lower sounds.
Um and in heaven it's deeper, right?
Slower vibrations. So harder sounds as
well. It It
And like having not known anything about
Italian, okay? That's my guess.
>> Yeah, I remember I actually had to learn
a little bit of the Inferno. And I just
The only lines I remember is like
It's like "Cred'io che credette ch'io
credesse che tutti i vo' ch'uci siate
per l'alto fiumana." It's like more
staccato.
>> And And you can do that by controlling
syllables. Okay, does that make sense?
There are some hard syllables and there
are some
So there are some hard consonants and
soft consonants, okay? This is all
intentional on his part. Okay? That's
That's how powerful this is. And again,
I I said this 2 days ago, but like
unless you truly understand Italian,
it's almost impossible to understand the
Divine Comedy.
All right? Uh yes?
>> Um so something I think Italian is
called uh Latin's master child. So
basically Italian is really close to
Latin and I've learned a little bit tiny
bit of Latin and Latin has like endings.
So basically you can see a lot of a a a
and these are all endings and I think it
makes it more
rhythmic almost. It makes it easier to
rhyme and makes it flow more smoothly
than English, which is all broken up and
has no endings.
>> Okay.
So, I have a question. So, uh
look at the text in every tercet,
the last sound of the first sentence and
the last sound of the last sentence
actually always rhyme.
And
is there any name for this kind of
cadence or, you know,
rhyme
in the in the Italian literature?
And and by reading English, you cannot
get this. You know, it's it's not rhyme.
>> I'm pretty sure there's some rhyme
translations in English, but they are
pretty bad. But I I think
I can't remember what it's called, but
>> Okay, so so so first of all, let me ask
you this question. This this is neither,
right?
>> Yeah.
>> Okay, can can can you explain the the
the the the meter scheme to for so so we
understand?
Can can can you actually write it down
for us? So so to
>> So like we can look at which syllables
are stressed and unstressed, but I
honestly
>> Okay, it's it's called neither, okay?
>> Okay.
>> Sorry.
So like
And love you too, can I swear to me and
do say. So it's like and love you too,
can I swear to me and do say. So it's
like every other syllable is stressed
and unstressed.
And love you too. So I'm pretty sure
I need to check my notes because I
literally was doing this like years ago,
but
>> So so another thing is this this is
music, okay? It's designed to be music.
Right? So in other words, the idea is
that you hear it once and it sticks in
your brain forever. You can sing it to
yourself.
Right? That's why
this became Tuscan became the official
language of of Italy over time. Okay?
All right. Okay, so let's let's let's
continue, guys. Okay?
>> All right.
Verse 103.
But she who saw what my desire was, her
smile had so much gladness that within
her face there seemed to be God's joy
began. The nature of the universe which
holds the center still and moves all
else around it begins here as if from
its turning post. This heaven has no
other where than this, the mind of God,
in which are kindled both the love that
turns it and the force it reigns.
>> Um
so, let let me ask you this.
Um
is a language which in towards a sexual
climax? It it It's a weird question, but
like
do you think this language is moving
towards a sexual climax?
>> I'm not sure if sexual, but maybe. I
mean, it's she's he's talking about
desire, right? There's gladness. Like it
feels very like that's kind of what he's
talking about.
>> Okay. So, this
is
really
uh I think I think the language is
designed in to in order to
demonstrate, to illustrate the
conjoining the con- cut the total
intertwining of souls together, okay?
It's almost like a sexual union, a
sexual climax where they've had this
very long journey together. They've had
many adventures. They've been through a
lot of obstacles. And now that they've
reached the end they can now finally
make love to each other, okay?
Okay?
But is that mirrored in the language in
any way?
>> Yeah, I feel like I mean, honestly I do
feel like there's like the sibilance
that I mentioned earlier and I feel like
there's
the
Also, something I noticed earlier is
like the way that the Italian words have
I feel like uh meanings that come
through. They have similar sounds in
English in Italian that don't come
through in English. So, there's like one
part where it says donna and donna. So,
donna means woman, donna is like to
give. So, there's like I feel like
overlapping in meanings in some of the
some of the sounds. And then also, okay,
I just looked it up. Terza rima is the
form the rhyme scheme that you mentioned
earlier, David. So, like I think the
terza rima also has something in there
that builds to a climax just because
it's like three lines, ABA, you know,
BCB, and then continuing on and then
ending in this couplet. So, I feel like
there is something that's like moving
towards something in just the rhyme
scheme.
>> Yeah, I mean like just trying to figure
out what he's trying to do, it seems as
though he's trying to to express the
consummation of this love but between
Beatrice and Dante. Yes?
>> Uh I think this is also very biblical
because in a lot of Jesus uh sermon on
the mount or whatever, like there were a
lot of wedding things that's talked
about. Yeah.
>> Yeah, this is almost like a wedding.
Yeah.
Yeah, thank you so much. That That's a
great point. Yes?
>> Uh this is again my personal feeling,
but I think that uh this is more like
these two uh both joining God and maybe
joining together in the process than the
two of them like joining together
separately because
uh before this like before this climax,
there's like so many mentions of uh
Beatrice looking towards God like uh
she's his bride, and of uh Dante looking
towards Beatrice not Beatrice is so
beautiful, but God is shining for
Beatrice, and God is so beautiful. So,
maybe they're all both joining together
in God, and that's what's making them
join, not separately.
>> Okay. Yeah. Okay. So, yes, you need to
love someone in order to reach God reach
to God. Yes?
>> Yeah, I have a question. So, like you
mentioned how they have this like kind
of like sexual resonance before between
like Beatrice and Dante, and I know like
misordered sex is considered as sinful,
and I like why are they justified for
having these sorts of like resonance? Is
it because it's leveled up from like
physical to like a more spiritual level?
Or
>> Okay. So, again,
uh Dante is a heretic. He is not going
to follow church theology.
And
um
the
the sexual nature of this language, what
what is it trying to do, do you think?
What was the point of this sexual
language? What what what is its its
effect on on the reader? Yes?
>> It's a universal language, and the
reader is meant to understand it.
>> Okay. Yes.
>> It represents the beginning of closest
to climax, aka getting closer to God.
>> Exactly. Okay. The sex is meant to
represent God.
It doesn't make sense to you guys? Okay.
Because sex what what it is is the union
of all things.
Okay? All right. So, so, so, so, as we
are moving towards God, there has to be
the unity of Beatrice and Dante in order
for Dante to fully proceed because
when you when you approach God, you have
to do it by yourself. Beatrice won't be
there. As as I said, it's it's
impossible for two people to be with
God. You only you can do it. Uh yes?
>> I'm like I'm reminded of this this
Catholic custom of
uh limiting the days on which even
marital sex can be undertaken. Like it's
severely limited. Like no Sundays, no
Lent, no Easter. And maybe uh this is a
very this is an anachronistic stretch,
but maybe Dante here is advocating for
not a free, but at least a freer
approach to human sexuality than what
the church encourages.
>> There's very very little
sex in the Divine Comedy. Uh
so
Okay. Uh yes?
>> I think that take is saying that sex is
more physical than it is spiritual.
>> Yes. Yes. Uh
Dante is advocating for a spiritual
union, okay? All right, but but but
let's let's let's keep on going, all
right?
>> Verse 112.
As in a circle light and love enclose it
as it surrounds the rest, and that
enclosing only he who encloses
understands. No other heaven measures
this sphere's motion, but it serves as
the measure for the rest even as half
and fifth determine 10. And now it can
be evident to you how time has roots
within this vessel and within the other
vessels has its leaves.
>> Luce e amor d'un cerchio lui comprende,
sì come questo li altri, e quel precinto
colui che il
cinge solamente intende.
Non è moto per l'a- per altro distinto,
>> Okay. So what I want to point out is
that it's it you can read the poem from
infinite angles, okay? So there is the
Italian
language which provides insight. There
are these biblical references.
Um
but
also something that people don't
appreciate is the alchemy embedded
within the Divine Comedy, okay? And what
I mean by that is that
I don't know for sure, but but Dante was
probably a member of of a secret
society.
And guys, the point of a secret society
is not to engage in world domination,
okay?
The point of a secret society at this
point in history is to engage in
intellectual speculation, which includes
alchemy, which is, you know, their form
of chemistry. And if you just read this
really, really closely, you can see how
this is almost a formula for blending in
different elements together to create a
new
uh substance, okay?
All right? So and and there are all
these occult elements as well. Okay, so
I just point this out. We we don't have
to go into it because I don't know about
I don't I don't know enough about
alchemy to actually encyclopedia,
but I'm just saying how Divine Comedy it
provides lifetime of endless study from
multiple
uh angles, okay? All right. Let's keep
on going.
>> Verse 1 2 1.
Oh
you who within your depths cause mortals
to sink so that none is left able to
lift his eyes above your waves.
The will has a good blossoming in men,
but then the never-ending downpours turn
the sound plums into rotten empty skins.
For innocence and trust are to be found
only in little children, then they flee
even before full beard cloaks the
cheeks.
>> Okay, so you can just hear the sounds
and even not knowing the language, I
don't know the language, but you don't
you don't really feel the sadness,
the pity, the poignancy in the tone,
right? Where
Dante, Beatrice, they are now up with
God and they can look down below and see
the folly,
the silliness,
the shortsightedness of the human
of of humans, right?
Okay? Where humans insist on fighting
for
almost nothing in our world and they
abandon the spiritual pleasures of a
higher world, okay? It's it's it's a it
it it sounds like pity. It sounds like
um
uh
what
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yes.
>> Oh, yeah, I agree. It sounds like a
lament. And also, I wanted to ask like
uh
we know that in history this time this
is the time when Italy was embroiled in
turmoil [cough]
and in war. So, could this be Dante's
call for his age to stop fighting with
each other and start uniting towards
peace and greater understanding.
>> Um no, he's calling for greater
enlightenment.
He's calling for the recognition of the
infiniteness, the
vastness of the cosmos, okay? That's the
secret. But asking for peace does you no
good. What What people need to recognize
What What people need to do is expand
their imagination, expand their sight.
Okay? That's what That's what what he's
literally calling for, okay? And And And
And And we'll see that as we go on,
okay? Let's keep on going.
>> Line 130.
One, for as long as he still lisps, will
fast. But when his tongue is free at
last, he, gorgeous, devouring any food
through any mouth. And one, while he
still lisps, will love and heed his
mother. But when he acquires speech more
fully, he will long to see her buried.
Just so white skin turns black when it
is struck by direct light. The lovely
daughter of the one who brings us dawn
and leaves us evening.
>> Okay, let's keep on going.
>> Verse 139.
That you not be amazed at what I say,
consider this, on Earth no king holds
sway. Therefore, the family of humans
strays. But well before 1,000 years have
passed, and January's un-wintered by
day's hundredth part, which they neglect
below, this high sphere shall shine so
that Providence long awaited for will
turn the sterns to where the prows now
are, so that the fleet runs straight,
and then fine fruit shall follow on the
flower.
>> Okay, so
another thing that I'll point out is
that astrology astronomy are very
important in your life. Call me. Again,
I don't know astrology, so I can't
comment, but you you can see these
see astrology, okay? And what And what
astrology really is is the cyclical
movement of the universe. So, does a
language capture
cyclical movement? Are you able to
feel and hear
the cyclical movement?
Spherical movement in the words.
>> I think like outside of what we already
talked about is the rhyme scheme
returning.
I think
there is kind of maybe we can see a
little bit more
of the openness and the O's and like a
certain kind of roundness, I think in
some of the vowels that end these So
svernine il letta. I feel like it's a
little bit more pop e volgerà u'son le
prore. And then the fiore. Like I feel
like there maybe is like a circularity
just to those. And definitely a blooming
and like a return I feel like to the
seasons with the cyclicality.
>> Okay.
So, do you guys understand what's
happening here? Okay? I'm just making
these assumptions just trying to figure
out what you're trying to say, right?
And what would you what if you guys
actually know the Italian, what will
happen is the meaning is actually
captured in the language itself.
Okay? So, that as you hear the language,
images appear before you subconsciously.
And it and it it it excites your
connection to the divine.
Okay? All right. So, let's keep on
going.
>> Canto 28.
After the lady who imparadises my mind
disclosed the truth that is unlike the
present life of miserable mop mortals.
Then just as one who sees a mirrored
flame, its double candle stands behind
his back even before he thought of it or
gazed directly at it and he turns to
gauge if that glass tells the truth to
him and sees that it accords like voice
and instrument.
>> Wait, stop. Okay, all right. Um
this is this is important, okay? Um does
it any anyone remember
where we saw a mirrored flame before? A
mirrored flame.
This is actually very important for for
the ending, okay? So, I I draw your
attention to this. A mirror flame, a
flame in a mirror.
Where did we see this before?
>> Like during the experiment when like
they discussed the dark spots on the
moon.
>> Exactly. Do you remember where
Beatrice is trying to prove to Dante
that brightness is just as bright no
matter no matter the distance, right?
And so they construct this experiment
where there are three mirrors and you
hold a hold a light, a candle, and the
brightness is still as bright anywhere
anywhere. The The size might be
different, but the brightness is still
the same. Okay? I want you to remember
this because
um
this is the metaphor for God that Dante
will use at the very end of the Divine
Comedy, okay? The mirror flame. Okay,
keep on going.
>> Verse 10.
So does my memory recall. I did after I
looked into the lovely eyes of which
love made the noose that holds me tight.
And when I turned and my own eyes were
met by what appears within that sphere
whenever one looks intently at its
revolution.
I saw a point that sent forth so acute a
light that anyone who faced the force
with which it blazed would have to shut
his eyes.
>> Okay, so um
something that we didn't want to feel as
to appreciate is that
what Dante is telling us here is that
what is at the center of the universe?
Mhm?
>> God.
>> God, okay?
Okay? Do you understand this?
At the very center at the of the
universe
it's God. So, everything in the universe
is emanating from God, right?
Okay?
Okay, keep on going.
>> Verse 19.
And any star that seen from Earth would
seem to be the smallest set beside that
point as star conjoint with star would
seem a moon.
Around that point a ring of fire
wheeled, a ring perhaps as far from that
point as a halo from the star that
colors it.
When mist that forms the halo is most
thick, it wheeled so quickly that it
would outstrip the motion that most
swiftly girds the world.
Verse 28.
That ring was circled by a second ring,
the second by a third, third by a
fourth, fourth by a fifth, and fifth
ring by a sixth. Beyond the seventh ring
which followed was so wide that all of
Juno's messenger would be too narrow to
contain that circle. The eighth and
ninth were wider still, and each, even
as greater distance lay between it and
the first ring moved with lesser speed.
>> Okay, so um
let let me point this out where
the poetry is written in meter. It's
It's written in rhyme
as a way to express the mathematical
beauty and structure of the universe
itself.
Okay? Does that make sense to you guys?
Where the poetry, the language, the
construction
uh
of the meter, it's meant to mirror
the symmetrical structure of the
universe. Okay? It is
that true here? Okay, can you explain?
>> Yeah, I think the the way that we saw
how it was written.
Uh you know, it was
I think he's really trying to overwhelm
us with the numbers, right?
He's kind of trying to I think reflect
in this kind of overwhelming
uh rhythmic rhythmic and rhyming vision
reflect what the universe is structured
like and how beautiful this kind of
symmetry is.
>> So So, it's interesting, okay, because
like
um we are doing We're We are We are
reading this poetry wrong because poetry
is not meant to be read, okay? It's
meant to be heard and spoken. So, when
Dante was writing his poetry, guess
what, guys? He didn't He was not writing
the poetry. He was speaking it. He was
singing it. And you guys understand
this, okay?
So,
uh we're looking at it, and really it
was always meant to be heard and spoken.
Uh and that's really the great failing
of, I think, um literary education
nowadays, where we actually try to read
the poetry when it was actually meant to
be read aloud. Okay? All right. Uh let's
move on away.
>> Verse 37.
And I believe the ring with clearest
flame was that which lay least far from
the pure spark, because it shares most
deeply that point's truth.
My lady, who saw my perplexity, I was in
such suspense, said, "On that point
depend the heavens and the whole of
nature. Look at the circle that is
nearest it, and know its revolutions are
so swift because of burning love that
urges it."
Verse 46.
And I to her, "If Earth and the nine
spheres were ordered like those rings,
then I would be content with what you
have set out before me. But in the world
of sense, what one can see are spheres
becoming even more divine as they are
set at more distant from the center.
Thus, if my longing is to gain its end
in this amazing and angelic temple that
has as boundaries only love and light,
then I still have to hear just how the
model and copy do not share in one same
plan, for by myself I think on this in
vain.
>> Okay, so there there's a paradox here,
right? Where what Dante sees is God is
at the center of the universe and from
there everything else emanates outwards,
vibrates outwards. And obviously the
closer to God you are, the faster you
spin, the faster you you vibrate because
you burn for your desire to be closer to
God. And as you move out, it's almost
like people lose faith, they lose hope
um and they spin um more slow, they're
more lethargic, okay? That's what he's
seeing, but in our world, in the world
of senses, uh it's the opposite where if
you just look out in the night sky, it
seems as as though the further you are
uh
the faster and also the more holy, the
more divine it seems. So, how can we go
about explaining this contradiction,
okay? So, based on what we've learned,
what's the answer?
>> Uh yes.
Well, I mean I would say that it doesn't
make a difference because God is
everywhere and anywhere. So, like the
sun
shines everywhere and every spot. So,
you can still feel God.
>> [clears throat]
>> For example, like a metaphor.
>> Okay, good. Okay.
All right.
God is everywhere.
So, there's really no center. God we are
the center, yes?
Okay?
Any other possibilities?
Based on on what we've learned, with
what we've discussed.
All right. So, she'll tell us, okay?
Well, let's go on with it.
>> Verse 58.
You need not wonder if your fingers are
unable to undo that knot. No one has
tried, and so that knot is tightened,
taught,
my lady said, and then continued, "If
you would be satisfied, take what I tell
you, and let your mind be sharp as I
explain. The size of spheres of matter,
large and small larger small, depends
upon the power, more or less, that
spreads throughout their parts.
More excellence yields greater
blessedness. More blessedness must
comprehend a greater body when that
body's parts are equally complete."
>> Let's
Let's just finish her her Yeah, her
speech.
>> "And thus the sphere, which sweeps along
with it the rest of all the universe,
must match the circle that loves most
and knows the most. So, that if you but
draw your measure around the power
within, and not the semblance of the
angels that appear to you as circles,
you will discern a wonderful chord
between each sphere and its
intelligence. Greater chords with more
smaller with less.
Okay, so what's the answer?
What did she say?
How can I explain the paradox where
in
this realm
uh in the spiritual realm, God is center
of the universe, but in our realm it's
almost the opposite, right? Where we are
center of the universe and everything
else expands [clears throat] outwards.
So God is almost far away from us.
Right? How Yes?
>> Different perspectives. We are looking
at God one way, God's looking at us uh
whatever.
>> Well, it's definitely different
perspectives.
Right? But
Anyone?
What's going on What's going on here?
Yes?
>> The we we can become the center center
of this universe in the space all around
us.
>> And how do we become the center of the
universe?
Yes?
>> Um by becoming one with God who is the
center of the universe.
>> No, no, no. I'm saying how did we
develop the
uh geocentric model of the universe?
>> Oh.
Because
uh the Bible told us so.
>> Okay.
Okay.
No. Uh
No, it's I think it's Ptolemy who told
us so, right?
It's in the Bible.
Uh
>> The the logic here is that God created
the entire universe, but God likes
humans the best, and therefore he likes
the world that the humans live on the
best, and therefore Earth is the middle
of everything. I think that's kind of
how logic works.
>> Oh, okay. Well, well, um anyone else?
Okay.
Um
I think what he's trying to say is that
we live in a world of illusion.
Okay? Everything you see with our eyes
is all just things we made up.
Uh it's all an illusion. Okay? It's all
a product of our imagination. Because
our imagination can both reveal the
truth to us, but it can also lie to us.
Okay? Does that make sense?
Okay? But if you really want to know the
true nature of the universe,
feel with your heart.
Okay? Feel with your heart.
Feel your soul. If you do that, you will
know that God [clears throat] must be at
the center of the universe,
and those that
are most
loyal to him, those that um are most
virtuous, are closer to him than those
who are not as
uh virtuous.
Okay? That's the truth.
So, our eyes lie to us.
But, our heart will not lie to us.
Does that make sense, guys?
Any other Any other explanations do you
do you think? Yes?
>> Uh, yeah. I have a question because uh,
we don't know where the heart is. Uh,
because some people say the heart
>> Our heart is
>> part of your chest or heart of your mind
or
>> No, your heart is your intuition, right?
It's what you feel to be right.
Okay?
Does that make sense?
It's like what you know to be right.
It's not what you see to be right, it's
what you know to uh, be right.
Okay?
Any any other questions? Yes?
>> Um,
like
these like these lines seem to like
discuss the matter of material and
spiritual
um, existence. So, to me I think it
seems to say that um, our eyes can only
perceive the material.
Um,
so, but that but that um,
the material actually aligns with the
spiritual in that
um,
the more
blessed
some something is, the more space it
takes up and um, the greater
>> the body is?
>> Not in our world, though. In the
spiritual world.
She's referring to the spiritual world,
right?
>> But, like
but like our eyes see things farther
away
as like
greater and bigger.
>> Wait. All right. Okay.
So, let me explain some some Kant to
you, Immanuel Kant, okay?
And this is his understanding of how we
perceive things.
So, Kant differentiates between
the noumena and the phenomena, okay?
Noumena Noumena is just things in
themselves.
Okay? And this is this is what we
Beatrice refers to as the spiritual
world, the real world, okay?
And then the phenomena are things to us,
phenomena.
Okay? So, how we interact with reality
is we see the noumena and then we filter
it
through time and space.
And we see the phenomena. So, we can
never actually see the noumena.
Okay?
So,
the only way that you can actually see
the noumena is with your heart,
with with your faith.
Does that make sense? And and and And
that's what Beatrice is really saying
here.
Okay? Let me give you another example,
which is Plato's allegory of the cave.
Okay? Plato's allegor- allegory of the
cave is where
imagine
prisoners, a million of them,
chained
to a floor in a cave.
And they can only see what's in front of
them, which is a wall, an empty wall,
right? Behind them is this fire and you
have these people who project shadows
onto the wall with this fire.
And you know this to be reality.
But then one prisoner escapes and he
goes out into the light and he sees the
totality of the universe, he sees the
sun, and he sees that the world that
we're living in is
false, okay? So, that's So, that's what
Beatrice is saying. Beatrice is saying
there are two realities. There's a real
reality, the noumena, and then there's
there's a world that we perceive,
phenomena.
And so, the question then is, how can
you escape into
the light? What propels you into the
light?
And the answer, of course, is love.
Okay?
Uh
Tony's love for Beatrice is what carries
him through the cosmos and into the
light.
Okay, does that make sense?
Uh yes?
>> Uh maybe another way of um
uh
cons- reconciling this uh you know, this
distance versus uh center
uh paradox is uh to view God not as uh
uh
a singularity or or a point, but a
comprehensiveness or com- uh you know,
uh so, basically,
>> [clears throat]
>> the bigger the scheme,
the closer we are to God. So, the God is
really the most comprehensive, the most
in you know, uh permissive uh per-
permeative, which means this uh the God
uh actually is the biggest scheme,
and it's everywhere and nowhere. So,
the further we look, the maybe, you
know, from the human point of view, the
you know, the bigger scheme we have in
our eyes,
the closer we are to God.
>> Okay, yeah, good. Good.
Right.
Uh anyone else? Did Did Did you have a
question or
>> Uh yeah, I still have question because
the love is uh I don't know what is love
really true love is. It it If If you
mean the true love which is soul
soulmate, just which can cause love or
just using the the sex the sexuality
there which can cause love.
>> Uh love is something you don't you don't
explain. Something Love is something
that you do. Love is something you
experience, right?
A mother's love for her child,
right? It's all It's unconditional
giving of yourself to someone else.
Okay, uh Did Did you have a question,
yes?
>> Yeah, I just want to ask does human
intrinsically have
how their intuition to observe or
knowing what's really nominal is?
>> Okay.
Um
So
When we When we appreciate what's going
on
is that the soul
uh is infinite, okay? What I mean by
that is that it is existing in different
dimensions all at once.
So
uh you think that
all that you see before you is what's
real, okay? But there's a higher part of
you that is also experiencing the
spiritual world. Okay? So
um
your soul is fragmented across infinite
dimensions. And the soul is experiencing
different things at at once.
But you bring yourself to focus only on
the here here and now. So when you
engage in psychedelics, when you engage
in meditation,
uh you're able to experience
different aspects of your soul, okay? If
that makes any sense.
>> Yeah. So
but I feel I just don't understand
because for us we're like human, we are
limited by the time and space, right? So
uh when we
>> No, you're not. Your perception is
limited by time and space. You are not.
Okay, so
>> So okay. So So let's say my perception
is limited by the time and my uh
by the time and space and like
my eyes will be deceived, right?
Maybe this is to find the truth. So
uh you're saying that
um if I could be like deceived by or
limited by my perception
like how could I just uh convey the true
message into my into myself who are who
are stay at the higher layer, you know.
Because since since like for me I can
only
receive the information from
>> Right. So so we were discussing this
like all the time, okay? Use your
imagination, use your intuition, act
with
faith, hope, and love.
>> Yeah.
>> And then the soul aligns itself.
Okay, does that make sense?
>> Yeah, I know. So I just
uh
quite feel confused about the
relationship between the soul and the
perception because I think sometimes my
I mean, in order to make the decision my
soul like needs some information from my
perception. Is that right?
Because I don't think I can
intrinsically have those skills to know
what is like right for me of my soul.
>> Okay. All right. This is how the
universe is structured, okay?
All right.
Okay, this is hard to understand, but
let's just say
there's
infinite number of us, okay?
What's happening is that your soul is
infinite. It travels across multiple
dimensions, right?
So what's happening is that
depending on on the dimension
your alignment with others is different,
right? Here you are by yourself, here
you are with another person. Blah blah.
This goes on for infinity.
Okay, does that make sense?
And what you're what you're doing is
you're focusing on the here and now, and
so what you're doing is you put you
think that this is the only reality,
when in fact it's only a small fragment
of of your total reality.
Okay?
>> Yeah.
>> All right. Okay. Uh
let's let's let's continue. And um for
uh we we we we don't have hour just
because we're we're in a rush. Uh we
don't have to hear the Italian more.
Let's let let Yeah, let let us um
read in English. Yeah.
>> Verse 79.
Just as the hemisphere of air remains
splendid, serene when from his gentler
cheek Boreas blows and clears the sky,
dissolves the mist that had defaced the
sky, so that the heavens smile with
loveliness in all their regions, even so
did I become after my lady had supplied
her clear response to me, and like a
star in heaven truth was seen. And when
her words were done, even as
incandescent iron will shower sparks, so
did those circles sparkle, and in each
spark circled with its flaming ring.
>> Okay, um what is
interesting about this language?
What
What is strange about this
language? And it it it's new to us.
What's What's What sentence stands out
to you?
What sentence stands out to you as
as
weird or
confusing?
This didn't happen before, but it's
happening now that we are closer to God.
Yes, go ahead.
>> Uh
line 88 to 90 is like the orgasm.
>> Mhm.
Right.
>> Where's the Where's the What's the line?
>> Yeah, can you can you explain to her cuz
it's
>> Okay.
Um
Well,
um Beatrice supplied her clear response
to Dante
and like a star in heaven, truth was
seen. And when her words were done, even
in as incandescent iron will shower
sparks, so did those circles sparkle.
And each spark circle circled with its
flaming ray.
>> Yeah. Can you guys uh Can you guys
understand this thing? The heavens smile
with loveliness.
Okay, this is really important
I I didn't understand, okay? Where you
have now reached Empyrean. And so there
is a total unity of everything. So
whatever you do is reflected throughout
the cosmos. You understand? So if you
say something and you smile
and you're happy, the heavens smile with
you.
Does that make sense?
Okay?
And this actually is mirrored throughout
the universe, but it is less obvious.
But now that we are at the very core,
whatever you do is now reflected
throughout the universe.
Okay? If you smile, the heavens smile
with you.
Um so even the most subtle thing can
have a huge impact throughout the
universe. It does look like the
butterfly effect, okay? And we're seeing
it manifest itself here.
Does that make sense to you guys?
Okay, let let let's keep on going.
>> Sparks that were more in number than the
sum one reaches, doubling in succession
each square of a chessboard, 1 to 64. I
heard Hosanna sung from choir to choir
to that fixed point which holds and
always shall hold them to where they
have forever been.
And she who saw my mind's perplexity
said, "The first circles have displayed
to you the seraphim and cherubim. They
follow the ties of love with such
rapidity because they're as like the
point of scriptures can be a power
dependent on their vision. Those other
loves that circle round them are called
thrones of the divine aspect because
they terminated at the first group of
three and know that all delight to the
degree to which their vision sees more
or less deeply that truth in which all
intellects find rest. From this you see
that less than this depends upon the act
of vision not upon the act of love which
is a consequence. The measure of their
vision lies in merit produced by grace
and then by will to goodness and this is
the progression step by step.
The second triad blossoming in this
eternal springtime that the nightly ram
does not despoil perpetually sings
Hosanna with three melodies that sound
in the three ranks of bliss that form
this triad. Within this hierarchy there
there are three kinds of divinities.
First the dominions and then the virtues
and the final order contains the powers.
The two penultimate groups of rejoicing
ones within the next triad are wheeling
principalities and then archangels.
Last the playful angels.
These orders all direct ecstatically
their eyes on high and downward they
exert such force that all are drawn and
draw to God and
Dionysius with much longing set himself
to contemplate these orders. He named
and distinguished them just as I do.
Though later Gregory disputed them when
Gregory came here when he could see with
opened eyes he smiled at his mistake.
You need not wonder if a mortal told
such secret truth on earth. It was
disclosed to him by one who sought here
above both that and other truths about
these circles.
>> Wait, so this is a hard question, okay?
But but but but let's but let me ask you
and see what happens.
So, here we are in Imperium.
And in Imperium are the angels. And
there are different orders of angels.
And
um these are perfect beings, okay?
What
How is Dante describing the structure of
the Imperium? What analogy can we use
this to
um ex- to
explain Dante's understanding of the
Imperium? He It's It's It's If you read
the language carefully, he is borrowing
um a language, a structure from where?
Yes?
>> Well, you're probably saying that I'm
wrong again, but I think this actually
reminds me a lot of the circles of hell.
>> The circles of hell?
>> Yes, because circles upon circles upon
circles. Less than living creatures.
>> Okay, let me ask you this question.
Do you think that these angels
are conscious?
>> Yeah, that's that's that's a problem,
isn't it?
That's the problem. Like, if they love
God so much, if they're incapable of
sinning, then do they truly have free
will?
>> Yeah. So, so what is this
analogy of? What Like Like let's think
about your life and the universe, okay?
The The script- The script in here
describes
what?
Really?
>> Solar system?
>> The solar system, yes, okay. Yes, the
solar system, the movement of the stars,
it's all
Yes, that's one possibility.
But I'm actually think- think- thinking
of something else. Yes?
>> I think this is looks like brain, you
know, if you in your in your head and
brain seems like
>> Yeah, it's almost your body, right? It's
almost like these angels are different
organs in your body. They have actually
no free will. They have no
consciousness. They have a function. And
there's And there's And they are exist
for a different reason. And they must
exist together in order to maintain the
functioning of the body, but by
themselves they have absolutely no free
will.
And this is a This is paradox. This is
extreme paradox in here if you if you
are a Catholic
theologian. Why would Why would this be
an extreme paradox for you?
What are angels?
What do angels represent?
>> Um they represent like uh dead people.
Like your soul goes into heaven and you
become an angel.
>> Come on.
>> The messengers of God.
>> To me?
>> Why Why are they messengers of God? What
What What do they represent? When you
think of an angel, what what Like like
like how do you imagine the angel to be?
>> Like
good virtues.
>> Yes, virtuous, right?
>> Yeah.
>> Okay.
What else?
Virtuous.
Perfection, right?
You mean [snorts]
So, here's a question for you then.
Are these angels being presented in a
positive light in The Divine Comedy?
We think of angels as virtuous as
perfect, but here
like do you want to be an angel?
>> No.
>> Not really.
This is a paradox being created for us,
right?
Right? I mean
you're taught to worship angels. You're
taught to believe that angels are higher
than you,
but you read this and it almost seems
like angels are just part of a political
system that have absolutely no free
will,
no consciousness, no purpose. I mean
they have a purpose, but it's not it's
not anything that they can control. They
don't actually know free will.
It doesn't make Yeah?
>> But I guess maybe um
Maybe maybe a Catholic would argue or
somebody who thinks
>> Somebody wants to defend the angels
might say, "Oh, but because they're
perfectly united with God, they have
kind of have the perfect expression of
free will. Like they're the most free
because they are free of sin. They don't
have to worry about ending up in hell
and being chained up for the rest of
your life. They They are fully free
because they partake fully in the
knowledge of God."
>> Yeah, that's a great point. So, they are
free because they can make no mistakes,
right? They're perfect. So, so what what
we know about the angels is and and he
just tells us is like Remember, the idea
is that God is calling to you and you
want to return to God, but it's your
choice whether to turn to God or to turn
away from God, right? And here the
angels
are always turning towards God. Okay?
So, they reach perfection. But my
question
My question is that Do you think that
Dante thinks this is a good thing or a
bad thing?
Right? Like like I I understand the
argument, okay? But I'm just saying like
for Dante, is this a good thing or bad
thing in that you are always turning
towards God? Yes?
>> Um bad thing.
>> But how Why?
>> They lack imagination.
They lack the ability to imagine and
that for the lack of ability to truly
and not just to love.
They're not able to love.
>> Yeah, they they lack consciousness,
right?
Okay, we think consciousness is a good
thing.
Um
But but but but but again, I mean like
like you can argue like what these
angels represent is perfection, right?
So, when you
um truly embrace God, you're always
turning towards God and you then lose
consciousness. So, it's a really weird
idea to think about, right? We're huh.
So, we're taught to be perfect, we're
taught to be virtuous, but that just
leads us to
losing our imagination, loses our
consciousness.
This is a really
troubling understanding.
Okay?
What's going on here?
But do we do we agree that that that
this is what's happening here?
Okay?
But um
not only do the angels
they lack imagination, they lack
consciousness,
they lack they lack something even more
fundamental.
And what they lack is
memory.
They don't remember anything.
Why?
>> They haven't experienced.
>> They have Yeah, go ahead.
>> Sorry.
Sorry, I was about to say that they
can't feel like time and space and
memory I guess has is related to that.
>> Yeah, yeah, you're right. Okay, so
without time and space you can't have an
an experience. But but why would But why
would you remember an experience?
>> Uh it's when it's linked to an emotion.
>> Exactly.
>> to an experience with an emotion.
>> Yeah, you need the emotion, okay?
Without the emotion you don't have
memory. It's impossible if you're a
perfect virtuous being to have an
emotion because why would you get angry?
Why would you get sad? Why would you Why
would you cry?
Okay? So, this is a really strange
paradox because what it seems like what
Donny's really arguing for is the
perfection
of fallibility.
Do you understand this idea?
In other words,
our flaws, our hatred, our pain, our
agony
is what allows us to be perfect.
Okay?
Does that make sense?
The imperfection is what's perfection.
The perfection is the imperfection.
Again, Donny's one testament. I told you
what he's trying to propose is
revolutionary, it's shocking, it's
mind-blowing, okay? But I think
given how this is structured, this is
what he's trying to tell us.
Okay?
We come all the way and we are with the
angels and we recognize
these angels are kind of stupid,
actually.
Right?
You cannot engage in a serious
discussion with an angel. Angels would
come to this class and they would not
say anything.
Okay? They won't remember anything. Uh
yes?
>> Uh so, I have this comment on live
stream that really echoes with
uh
what Professor Johnson says. He says,
"Angels are servants of God. We are not
perfect and the beauty of human is in
his imperfection."
>> Yes, okay, yes, okay. Yeah, so, um
yes. I mean, you could argue like angels
are just servants of God, okay? They're
not meant to have free will, they're not
meant to be conscious, they're not meant
to have experiences. They're just meant
to ensure the ordering of the universe,
okay? They're just meant to ensure the
structure the proper structuring of the
of of the universe. They're like
minions.
All right?
But again, this goes against our
traditional understanding of
of things, right?
Okay, I mean, are you Catholic?
>> No.
>> Okay, but like
um
>> But I I'm happy to
pretend to be.
>> Okay, all right, okay, but like but like
um
like like hearing this, what
what do you think?
>> I wonder because I feel like there's a
kind of I feel like Dante expresses this
paradox throughout the whole project of
the of the Divine Comedy because we know
he's lost in the middle of a dark forest
at the very beginning and he's trying to
figure out, okay, how do I escape this
like terrible confusion that I feel,
which is what I feel like the student
brought up. I'm sorry, I don't know your
name.
But like this kind of confusion of what
do I what do I actually want if I want
kind of eternity, but also um that I
don't know what what my life is meant
for. And then I feel like here you're I
think you're so right that there is a
kind of
uh almost
I think we work up to this ecstatic
ending and it's just angels circling God
and it seems I think he is I think he's
being serious by presenting it as, okay,
this is beautiful and a wonderful vision
of perfection, but then also because
this is part of his journey, he is like
maybe I feel I wonder if he identifies
with Dionysus or Mercury in in this in
Beatrice's um
final explanation where he is also a
visitor passing through and he's seeing
this
and we know that
I think we should take the Divine Comedy
seriously. I don't think he's just
presenting it as an allegory. I think
he's like trying to say, I I witnessed
these things and I I bring them back to
you. Um but I do think there's a kind of
this is his journey from the darkness of
the forest and that these angels perhaps
do not relate to
>> Right. Yeah, so the idea is it's
confusion that can only that leads to
clarity, right?
Okay. Thank you. Okay. All right, let's
let's let's continue, okay? Um because I
really want to finish the Divine Comedy
uh
>> Oh, can I also just really quickly bring
up cuz I know another if somebody also
brought up August Augustine, I think
there's an interesting similarity with
Confessions with like this kind of oh,
I'm a fallible human. I kind of desire
perfection, but also not really. I think
there's of a weird Yeah.
>> Right. Okay. So, this is going to be
Canto 29, okay? And again,
Uh
yeah. Yeah.
Uh could you please read the Canto?
>> Canto 29.
As long as both the Thomas children
take, when covered by the ram and
scales, they make their belt at the
horizon at the same moment to pass from
equilibrium, the zenith held in balance,
to that state where changing hemispheres
as each leaves that belt, so long did
Beatrice, a smile upon her face, kept
silent, even as she gazed intently at
the point that overwhelmed me.
Then she began.
I tell, not ask, what you now want to
hear, for I have seen it there, where
and what point, oh whence and ubi
and
not to acquire new goodness for himself,
which cannot be, but that his splendor
might, as it shines back to him, declare
subsistence.
In his eternity outside of time, beyond
all other borders as pleased him,
eternal love opened into new loves. Nor
did he lie before this as if languid.
There was no after, no before. They were
not there until God moved upon these
waters.
Then form and matter, either separately
or in mixed state, emerged as flawless
being. As from a three-stringed bow,
three arrows sprang.
And as a ray shines into amber, crystal,
or glass, so that there's no interval
between its coming and its lighting,
also did the three, form, matter, and
their union, flash into being from the
Lord with no distinction in beginning,
all at once.
Created with the substances where order
and pattern. At the summit of the world
were those in whom pure act had been
produced. And pure potentiality
possessed the lowest part. And in the
middle, acts so joined potentiality that
they never disjoint. For you, Jerome has
written that the creation of the angels
came long centuries before all else were
made.
But this, the truth I speak, is written
by the scribes of the Holy Ghost, as you
can find if you look carefully on many
pages.
And reason, too, can see in part this
truth, for it would not admit that those
who moved the heavens could for so long
be without their perfect task.
Now you know where and when and how
these loving spirits were created. With
this,
three flames of your desire are
quenched.
Then, sooner than it takes to count to
20, a portion of the angels violently
disturbed the lowest of your elements.
The rest remained.
And they, with such rejoicing,
rejoicing, began the office you can see
that they never desert their circling
contemplation.
The fall had its beginning in the cursed
of pride of the one you saw, held in
constraint by all the world's weights.
Those whom you see in heaven here were
modestly aware that they were ready for
intelligence so vast because of that
good which had made them.
Through this, their vision was exalted
with illuminating grace and with their
merit, so that their will is constant
and intact.
I would not have you doubt, but have you
know surely that there's merit in
receiving grace measured by the longing
to receive it.
By now, if you have taken in my words,
you need no other aid to contemplate
much in regard to this consistory.
But since on Earth, throughout your
schools, they teach that it is in the
nature of angels to understand, to
recollect, to will, I shall say more so
that you may see clearly the truth that
there below has been confused by
teaching that is so ambiguous.
These beings, since they first were glad
by the face of God,
from which no thing is hidden, have
never turned their vision from that
face, so that their sight is never
intercepted by new a new object, and
they have no need to recollect an
interrupted concept.
>> Okay, so no need to recollect an
interrupted concept just means they have
to be no recollection, no memory of
anything, okay? Does that make sense to
you guys? No imagination, no memory,
just pure devotion, obedience to God.
Thank you. I'm going.
>> So that below, though not asleep, men
dream, speaking in good faith or in bad.
The last, however, merits greater blame
and shame.
Below you do not follow one sole path as
you philosophize. Your love of show and
thought of it so carry you astray. Yet
even love of show is suffered here with
less disdain than the subordination or
the perversion of the holy scripture.
There, they devote no thought how much
blood cost to sow it in the world, to
how pleasing is he who humbly holds it
fast. Each one strives for display,
elaborates its own inventions. Preachers
speak at length of these. Meanwhile, the
Gospels do not speak.
One says that to prevent the sun from
reaching below the moon when Christ was
crucified, moved back along the zodiac,
so as to interpose itself. Who says so,
lies, for sunlight hid itself. Not only
Jews, but Spaniards, Indians, too, saw
that eclipse.
Such fables, shouted through the year
from pulpits, some here, some there,
outnumber even all the Lapos and the
Bindos Florence has.
So that the Retichi and Ignorance return
from pasture, having fed on wind, but to
be blind to harm does does excuse them.
Christ did not say to his first company,
"Go and preach idle stories to the
world." But he gave them the teaching
that is truth, and truth alone was
sounded when they spoke. And thus to
battle to
and kindle faith, the gospel served them
as both shield and lance.
But now men go to preach with jests and
jeers, and just as long as they can
raise a laugh, the cow puffs up and
nothing more is asked.
But such a bird nests in that cow that
if people saw it, they would recognize
as lies the pardons in which they
confide, pardons through which the
world's credulity increases so that
people throng to every indulgence backed
by no authority. And this allows the
Antonines to fatten their pigs and
others too, more piggish still who pay
with counterfeit illegal tender.
But since we have digressed enough, turn
back your eyes now to the way that is
direct. Our time is short, so too must
be our path. The number of these angels
is so great that there has never been a
mortal speech or mortal thought that
named a sum so deep. And if you look at
that which is revealed by Daniel, you'll
see that while he mentions thousands, he
gives no number with precision.
The first light reaches them in ways as
many as are the angels to which it
conjoins itself as it illumines all of
them.
And this is why, because affection
follows the act of knowledge, the
intensity of love's sweetness appears
unequally. By now you see the height,
you see the breadth of the eternal
goodness. It has made so many mirrors
which divide its light. But as before,
its own self still is one.
>> Okay. All right. So So we'll just finish
with Canto 29. Then uh on Saturday we
break tomorrow, guys. Okay? We break
tomorrow.
Um and then we come back on
Saturday and then we just
plow through, okay?
Um, so on Saturday we'll finish the
Comedy uh, Paradise, okay? So, we'll
look at cantos 30, 31, 32, 33.
Um,
so what Beatrice is doing here is he's
contrasting the perfection
of the angels with the imperfection of
the humans, okay?
And
um,
do you guys want want to be an angel?
I don't think anyone Anyone who reads
this is like, I want to be an angel now,
okay? Because it seems to me that the
life of an angel is really, really
boring,
right? It's perfect, nothing ever
changes.
And Beatrice, you know, she's sort of
like complaining about how stupid humans
are and how we just screw everything up,
we don't really get anything.
But,
I don't think anyone uh, who
reads this comes with the impression
like, you know what, I should strive to
be an angel.
Okay?
So,
how do we explain
this paradox?
Beatrice is
um, saying how angels are perfect and
how angels can do no wrong. Um, she is
re- reiterating classical Catholic
theology,
but when we read this, our instinct is
our intuition is like, mm, I'd rather be
human, thank you very much.
What's going on here?
Uh, yes?
>> Yeah, I feel confused because Lucifer,
you know, Satan, who is also the at the
angel of God, right? So, if in Dante's
[clears throat] case it means
you do not always devoted to God the
holy, means you have to have your own
awareness and consciousness, so
do you think that he believed that the
Satan is is right?
Because Satan is just have their own
wilderness, you know.
>> you know, this is a really interesting
question, right? Because he does mention
that there is one angel who defied God,
who turned away from God, and as a
result, he was banished
to hell. And what's And this is
interesting because what's what what
what's going to happen is that Milton,
John Milton, is going to read this. And
he's going to come up with Paradise
Lost.
Which is in many ways a celebration of
Satan and his rebellion, okay? So, um
Divine Comedy is an inspirer uh Milton's
Paradise Lost. But
when we read Inferno,
what we will recognize is that there's
nothing glorious in the rebellion of
Satan.
Okay? Because here we're seeing angels
without consciousness, without free
will.
But when we actually meet
Satan,
Lucifer, in Inferno,
he's the same way. He has no
consciousness. He has no free will. He
has no agency,
okay? So, it's almost like And this is
like really really interesting to think
about. It's almost like he designed
angels, God designed angels, to lack
agency, to lack free will,
to lack imagination. Designed humans to
be the opposite, okay? So, who does God
love more?
Humans.
Okay?
It's a So, again, this is so
revolutionary to think about how angels
are the ones who serve God, who are the
ones by God. God has to deal with them
every single day, but God, who he truly
loves, are
we fallen, silly, stupid mortals.
Okay?
Um and again, it's
um
God
did not give the angels free will.
He gave humans free will.
And so that just proves that God loves
us more. Okay?
>> [snorts]
>> Okay? Does it make sense to you guys?
All right.
Any other Yes?
>> I mean back to the um earlier several
classes ago there was an analogy about
the game master and the game players,
right? So can I take this to be like God
didn't intend for his
his admins, his angels to to
to be part of this game, but the game or
rather the
whatever you did however the universe is
designed for, it was designed for the
generation of love and imagination by
the human beings, the human players.
>> Yeah, you know, I I think that's
correct. I I think the way to understand
this is that
um
God in his perfection,
he recognizes he has a problem, which is
that perfection is imperfection, right?
And so the only way to complete himself,
the only way to know himself, the only
way to extend himself is by creating
humans in his image.
And humans are imperfect, but that is
our perfection.
Because with our clumsiness, with our
silliness, yet our longing for God, we
will somehow extend the imagination of
the universe. We will extend the
boundaries of the universe and let God
know himself more, complete himself
more. And does that make sense?
Okay? So again, this is like
revolutionary at this time because
Augustine,
right, is preaching that we are sinful,
we are proud, we are evil.
And what Dante is saying is that no, we
are the most superior beings in the
world in the universe, okay? We are even
higher in elevation than God.
Okay? And then we when we read the end
of Divine Comedy, and this is like what
makes Dante
so shocking is that
Dante is going to show us he's superior
to God.
Okay?
Um
He's not better than God, but he has an
imagination, which allows him to do
things God cannot do.
So, that is the shocking end towards the
Divine Comedy.
Um
okay, does that make sense?
All right.
Yeah.
I like the ending is just so shocking,
so weird.
It Again, like I hate to say this, but
it's shocking for us living in the year
2026, but imagine in the year 1300,
okay?
How revolutionary this is.
And how he's able to do this
faith,
hope, and love.
Okay? So, he is the manifestation he's
the total expression of what it means to
have faith, love, and hope. And as a
result, that's why he was chosen to go
to heaven like Mary, like Jesus.
Okay?
All right. Okay, any more any more
questions?
Okay. Uh well, thank you so much for for
for today. I mean, I just hear being
able to hear Dante, okay?
It's It's It's It's the voice that makes
this divine, right? The sound that makes
this truly divine. And that's why we
call this Divine Comedy. Okay, so thank
you very much. Uh we will continue this
Saturday, okay?
>> [applause]